<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Os ossorianvm, or, A bone for a bishop to pick being a vindication of some passages in a treatise lately published, called Anti-cavalierisme, from the impertinant and importune exceptions of Gr. Williams, the author of the Grand rebellion, calling himselfe by the name of the L. Bishop of Ossory : wherein likewise, the malignitie of severall passages in the said Grand rebellion against the Parliament is discovered, and that question further cleared, how and in what sense kingly government may be said to be the ordinance of God, so that it may indifferently serve for an answer to that whole discourse / by the author of the sayd treatise of Anti-cavalierisme.</title>
            <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23576</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12184339</idno>
  <idno type="VID">197154</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240955088</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1185</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12184339</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 197154)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 244:E96, no 1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Os ossorianvm, or, A bone for a bishop to pick being a vindication of some passages in a treatise lately published, called Anti-cavalierisme, from the impertinant and importune exceptions of Gr. Williams, the author of the Grand rebellion, calling himselfe by the name of the L. Bishop of Ossory : wherein likewise, the malignitie of severall passages in the said Grand rebellion against the Parliament is discovered, and that question further cleared, how and in what sense kingly government may be said to be the ordinance of God, so that it may indifferently serve for an answer to that whole discourse / by the author of the sayd treatise of Anti-cavalierisme.</title>
                  <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Overton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Goodwin. cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665. --  Anti-cavalierisme.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Williams, Gryffith, 1589?-1672. --  Vindiciae regum, or, The grand rebellion.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:197154:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:197154:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>OS OSSORIANVM,</hi> OR A BONE FOR A BISHOP TO PICK: Being a VINDICATION of some passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in a Treatise lately published, called ANTI-CAVA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIERISME, from the impertinent and importune exceptions of GR: WILLIAMS, the Author of the <hi>Grand Rebellion:</hi> Calling himselfe by the name of the L. Bishop of OSSORY. <hi>Wherein Likewise,</hi> The Malignitie of severall passages in the said <hi>Grand Rebellion</hi> against the <hi>Parliament,</hi> is discovered; and that Question further cleared; How and in what sense Kingly Government may be said to be the Ordinance of <hi>GOD:</hi> So that it may indifferently serve for an Answer to that whole Discourse. By the Author of the sayd TREATISE of ANTI-CAVALIERISME.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HOSEA, 7. 3.</bibl>
               <hi>They make the King glad with their wickednesse, and the Princes with their lies.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>Non Praelati, sed Pilati. <bibl>
                  <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> 1643.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:197154:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:197154:2"/>
            <head>A BONE FOR A BISHOP TO PICK.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Country Proverbe is, that <hi>Good Ale ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wants a friend on the Bench:</hi> Nor doth any notable designe of the Divell, against Reformation, or the power of Religion, ever want a friend, or two (for faile) upon the Episcopall Chayre. The Author of the <hi>Grand Rebellion</hi> (a title fit for <hi>Gr: Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> L. Bishop of <hi>Ossory,</hi> be it a man with a Vizard or without, and of his own procuring) ingenuously confesseth, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. of his discourse, <hi>that we scarce read of any Rebellion, but some base Priests, the Chaplaines of the Divell, have begot it Habemus confitentem reum:</hi> out of his own mouth, or from his own pen, we may judge him. For the truth is, that there is no baser Priests, then base Bishops, as there is no baser drosse then that which flies highest and lyes uppermost upon the mettall: nor is there any ranke of men under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which furnish the Divell with Chaplaines more to his minde, better instructed for the Kingdom of darknesse, readier either to sing or say masse at his elbow in state, then these. And very true it is, as this <hi>Grand Rebellionist</hi> affirmeth, that <hi>we scarce</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:197154:3"/>
                  <hi>read of any Rebellion, but some of these base Priests have begot it.</hi> He that desires particular information hereof, at least as far as concernes the Rebellions begotten in this Land and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is desired to repaire to Mr. <hi>Prynn's</hi> late Collections, entituled, <hi>The Antipathie of the English Lordly Prelacie, both to Regall Monarchy, and civill unity:</hi> where he shall finde many Rebellions and mischievous plots against Kings, and all of them calling Bishops by that Name and title they so much affect, I meane, FATHERS.</p>
               <p>And whether the present distempers, distractions, calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and confusions, which shake the very foundations of this Kingdome and State at this day, amongst which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing our Hierarchicall Seer finds his <hi>Grand Rebellion,</hi> doe not relate unto his own order, as the principall founders and fomenters of them; I referre to the mature and impartiall consideration of all knowing men amongst us, that have not drunk away their Christian wits, or drown'd their principles of ingenuity, in the intoxicating cup of the Romish whore. That dangerous arrow of contention which was lately shot betweene the two Sister Nations, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> do not the world know that it was shot out of an Episcopall Bow? And who are those that have sown the seeds of that most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall and deplorable strife, now broken out into a devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flame between his Majesty and his people, but statizing Prelates, who by the waters of their base flattery falling down so abundantly from the mountaines of their pride, into the channell of Prerogative, have made it swell like <hi>Iordan</hi> in the time of Harvest when hee overfloweth his banks? If men should set themselves to powre contempt upon Princes, and to undermine the Thrones, yea or the lives themselves, of Kings: there is no method or practise of a more conexive importance, of a more precipitate tendency hereunto, then by exposing and rendring them obnoxious to the jealousie of God, by making them his compeer's, in Omniscience, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipresence, Omnipotencie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which one of the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall Classis (Dr. <hi>Corbet</hi> by Name,) late Bishop of <hi>Norwich)</hi> did in a publique Sermon at <hi>Pauls Crosse,</hi> not very many yeares since, investing Kings with all the Royalties of Heaven and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:197154:3"/> with all the incommunicable properties and excellencies of God. Men of this kind of addres unto Kings and Princes, and that through importune flatteries and Idolatrous admiration and adoration of Regall power, bereave them of all memory and thought of their being <hi>but men,</hi> compelling them to own and claime to themselves Prerogatives above the Moon, such as paralell, if not transcend, the Prerogatives of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: These are the men that cannot with justice count it any injury at all to them, to be look'd upon as the Grand Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and procurers of farre the greatest part of all the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, miseries and mischiefes whatsoever, whereby either the Honour, Crownes, or Lives of Princes are indangered. The <hi>maker</hi> of the Idol, is sayd to be <hi>the sparke that kindles the fire</hi> wherewith it is <hi>burnt and consumed,</hi> Esa. 2. 31. And he certainly is the greatest endammager, if not destroyer of Kings, that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See more of this Anti-ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val.</hi> p. 14. 15.</note> placeth their Thrones too neere the Throne of God, and that tamper with the hearts and consciences of men to adore I know not what an unknowne Deity in them.</p>
               <p>The World needs not my information, nor any mans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, that Prelates, especially of later times, have beene the Grand Corrupters of the loyalty of Kings unto God: and consequently by weakening their interests in Heaven, have withal weakened and shaken their interests likewise on earth, I meane in the hearts and affections of men.</p>
               <p>And whether this <hi>Gr: Williams</hi> hath not beene hard at worke upon the same occupation with his Prelaticall frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, I appeale to the sweat of his browes, and the complaint of his eye-lids for want of sleepe, whilst his Master-piece of <hi>Grand Rebellion</hi> was in hammering.</p>
               <p>It is no part of my intent to garble the bulk of his Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leticall discourse, or to sift out all the drosse and soyle therof, there being little said, but what hath (in effect) bin answered <hi>plus millies.</hi> I shall onely passe two or three briefe Observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, upon the generall carriage of the discourse; and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider with what dexterity or successe, hee hath stormed the Anti-Cavalier, in those particulars of his Discourse, which a man would think troubled him, and stood in his way more then all their fellowes, because of his furious assault made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:197154:4"/> them in particular. But the man (I suspect) was herein more cunning then passionate: Hee made choice of those passages to give answer unto not which most opposed him in his way, but which he conceived would best take the colour of an answer &amp; were likeliest to suffer an <hi>Eclipse</hi> of their light, by an interposition of some misty lines betweene the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings of men and them; that so his Readers, and Party, apprehending some things answered in the Discourse, might by the figure <hi>Synechdoche,</hi> and out of their abundant charity, presume the whole Treatise to be sufficiently answered. It may bee this Philo-Cavalier is of the house and linage of that Ancient Souldier in Plautus called Thraso who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents his providence and prudence in War, thus: <hi>quà illi pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabant maximè, ego fugiebam maxime:</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Where Men were fiercest in the fight,</l>
                  <l>I made away by swiftest flight.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Certaine I am that where the Anti-Cavalier is strongest and neerest the heart of his businesse, there this Philo-Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier comes not neere him by 40. foot.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:197154:4"/>
               <head>CAP. I. OBSERVATIONS CONCERNING The Discourse mentioned, called the <hi>Grand Rebellion</hi> in the Generall.</head>
               <p>FIrst, whereas the Author of this Discourse, pretends his Calculation onely for the Meridian of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Parliament sitting in his <hi>Episcopall See</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>at Kellken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, pag</hi> 66. acknowledging with a counterfeit and gracelesse modestie, <hi>the</hi> Parliament <hi>of</hi> England <hi>to be above his sphere, p.</hi> 63. yet evident it is, by the spirit that rules in the ayre of the whole discourse; that the <hi>Parliament at Kellkenny</hi> was but the shadow; and the <hi>Parliament of England the body,</hi> that he would have sacrificed upon the service of his <hi>Episcopall See;</hi> and that they are not the Rebells indeed, the Popish Rebells in <hi>Ireland</hi> that this <hi>Gr.</hi> mainely brands with the odious imputation of Rebellion; but the best and loyallest Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> who favour the proceedings of the Parliament here, as just and equall, (being by solemne Protestation unto God lately made; deepely bound hereunto) The malignity of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this kind are so virulent and strong of the poyson, that it eates through the vaile and covering of <hi>Kellkenny,</hi> and Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> which he casts over it in severall passages of his discourse: and plainely discovers it's bent against the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> See whether these lines be calculated for the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or Parliament and Parliament friends in <hi>England. Nemo repentè fit pessimus: But the wicked grow worse and worse: First you must lend, then you must give, if not, we will take: or if you deny your goods, we will have your bodies. So</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:197154:5"/>
                  <hi>at first, whatsoever we doe, it is for the King,</hi> &amp;c. p. 97. So againe p. 68. <hi>it is well knowne to all the world, that whatsoever this good King hath Suffered at the hands of his Subiects, it is for the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the true</hi> Protestant Religion, <hi>of the established lawes of this Kingdome, of those Reverend</hi> Bishops, <hi>Grave</hi> Doctors, <hi>and all the rest of the learned and Religious</hi> Clergie, <hi>that have ever maintained and will to the spilling of the last drop of their blood, defend this Truth against all</hi> Papists, <hi>and other</hi> Anabaptisticall Brownists <hi>and Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries whatsoever.</hi> In these and many other passages of His Pamphlet, <hi>quasi so ex suo indicio perit.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Much like a Rat, before he is aware.</l>
                  <l>He squeak's himselfe into a trapping snare.</l>
               </q>
               <p>By this observation it is evident, that though the man bee but a Diocesan Bishop, yet he is an Arch-dissembler, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropoliticall Politician. He shelter's himselfe behind <hi>Kelken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> and the Paliament there, as his Bullwarke: and let's flie at the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> hoping, that though God should prosper his owne Cause in their hand, yet <hi>Kelkenny</hi> and the Rebells in <hi>Ireland,</hi> will protect him from the sword of their Justice.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that is considerable in the generall Carriage of his Discourse, that the bent of his fiercenesse all along is only (or chiefly) against his owne Fancy or shadow, and that hee either purely mistakes or willingly dissembles the state of the question betweene him and his adversaries. For all that hee beats himselfe, and wearies his Reader to prove in his <hi>Grand Rebellion,</hi> as appeares from the very Title Page, is this, <hi>That it is no wayes lawfull for any private man, or any sort or degree of men whatsoever in the Kingdome, for any cause, or upon any pre-text, to rebell, take armes, and resist the authority of their lawfull King:</hi> Which is a position, wherein hee hath <hi>neminem contradicentem</hi> (to my knowledge) certaine I am, that neither the <hi>Anti-Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> nor the seditious Pamphleter (falsely so called by him, <hi>p.</hi> 97.) against whom notwithstanding he tyrannizeth with his pen as if he had borrowed it of the great <hi>Turke</hi> for the service have any thing in their writings, repugnant thereunto. If the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:197154:5"/> man had had a mind to have done any thing worthy of his Chaire upon this occasion, or to have convinced his adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of error, he should have grappled with this conclusion, &amp; laid it flat on its back; <hi>that its lawfull for Subiects to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the uttermost, against lawlesse Thieves and Murderers;</hi> or (which is the same) against those who without any lawfull Authority or warrant either from God or man, attempt by force to take from them either their goods, liberties, lives, freedome of Religion, or the like. But this conclusion, feeles not so much as the weight of his little finger. Or at least, he should have tried the dexterity and strength of his learning to make good this position; <hi>that it is not lawfull for a state, in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernesse and truth of respects to the honour and safety of their King, and for the safety of the Kingdome to remove the wicked from about his Throne, especially being notorious Malefactors and Delinquents against the Laws: and further by their desperate Counsels and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises, apparently endanger both King and Kingdome.</hi> It is true, the proofe of this assertion, had it bin never so substantially made, would not have reach'd home, would not have conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the unlawfullnesse of taking up Armes against those pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed Sons of <hi>Abaddon</hi> those Cavaliers, that lawlesly and causelesly make spoyle and havock dayly of the lives, liberties and goods, of the Subjects of this Kingdome: yet, would it have come ten degrees nearer the maine Question in hand between him and those that are contrarie-minded to him, and vindicated the sufficiencie and learning of the man at another manner of rate, then by a long, tedious, and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stuous discourse only to prove that the Sun is up at noon day, that lawfull Authority cannot lawfully be resisted.</p>
               <p>But I perceive the man is full of Bishop-Craft: he saw that as well the impugning of the former, as the making good of the latter Conclusion were pieces too hot for him to handle, and therefore very wisely leaves them for others to burne their fingers with, if they please. But intending chiefly (as it seems) to abuse the judgements and Consciences of the weaker and lesse considering sort of men, and to weaken their hand in their way, he blusters and thunders, and armes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with hell fire, to maintaine and prove such a conclusion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:197154:6"/> which such men may easily think concludes them both, and yet in deed and in truth doth nothing lesse then conclude either. For to prove that Theeves and Murderers, or the destroyers of a Land, may not lawfully be resisted, because the Authority of a lawfull King may not be resisted, is as if I should goe about to prove, the earth to be a lightsome body, because the Sun is such, or that <hi>Gr. Williams</hi> is a Papist, because the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> is such.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he that shall attentively reade the discourse men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and narrowly compare place with place, shall find the Authour ever and anon prevaricating with his cause, turning head upon himselfe, full of inconsistences and firce contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, reeling and staggering, playing up and down, driven to and againe,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nunc hûc nunc illûc, exemplo nubis aquosae.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg> i. e.
<lg>
                        <l>Much like a watrish Cloud, which somtimes hither</l>
                        <l>Is driven with the wind, and somtimes thither.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> so that his Reader may much better, and more easily judge what his maine drift is by his Bishoprick, then by his Book. And the truth is, that they that have a mind to be his through Adversaries, need no other grounds to justifie the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> and their Friends, and the Armes they have taken up, then those that are positively layd down by himselfe. Nay that which is yet more, he affirmes and grants many things, which, if themselves were justifiable, would justifie farre harder proceedings against Kings by their Subjects, then any he so much as chargeth the Parliament or their assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants with, against the King. He affirmeth p. 67. that <hi>He that is entrusted, cannot doe more then all they that doe intrust him.</hi> Doth it not follow cleerly from hence, that the King, being the great Fiduciarie of the Kingdome, and intrusted by the people, can no more oppose them, then they him? Besides, how agreeth this assertion but as harp and harrow with that other, p. 64. viz. <hi>that the King is</hi> major universis, <hi>greater then all his People taken together?</hi> Doubtlesse he that is greater (in power and Authority) then all, may lawfully doe more then all.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:197154:6"/>
               <p>Againe, p. 69. we have this fairly affrmed, <hi>that it is lawfull to recall a power given, when it is abused.</hi> Doth not the man (think you) hold the Deposition of Kings lawfull in case of abused power? especially granting, (as he doth, p. 65. <hi>that the power wherewith the King is invested, was, the Peoples, till they yeelded it up unto him</hi> Whether the man be of this judgement or no, I am sure his words are.</p>
               <p>Againe, p. 55. we have (all in effect, and almost <hi>in terminis)</hi> fairely granted, which either the Anti-Cavalier, or the Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Pamphleter (before mentioned) contend for, in these words. <hi>But for private robbers, God hath not placed them over us, nor commanded us to obey them, neither have they any right by any law, but the law of strength, to exact any thing of us: and therfore we are obliged by no law to yeild obedience unto them, neither are we hindred by any necessity either of rule or subjection, but that we may lawfully repell all the injuries they offer unto us.</hi> I suppose the man hath so much ingenuitie (though it be not Episcopall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity) as to abhorre to say, that God hath placed that vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous brood of Cavaliers in the Kings Army over us: neither hath he commanded us to obey them: therfore by his own cleare and full assertion, <hi>we are not hindred by any necessity either of rule or subjection, but that we may lawfully repell all the injuries they offer unto us.</hi> And this (I dare say) is the <hi>summa totalis</hi> of all the particulars in the Tract of Anti-Cavalierisme, if they were truly cast up.</p>
               <p>Againe, when he saith pag. 103. <hi>That people have no better remedy, when Kings are evill, then to pray unto God, that as he hath sent them in his fury, so he would take away in his mercy;</hi> doth he not preferre the praying down, the praying dead of Kings, before the praying of them righteous, gracious, or accepted with God? Doubtlesse there is not the least touch of any so bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a streyne against Kings, in any of the writeings so severely censured by him. Besides, he that recommends it <hi>as the best remedie that people have, when Kings are evill, to pray to God to take them away:</hi> doth he not hereby justifie the lawfullnesse of using other means also to effect it? There are very few things, if any at all, that may lawfully be prayed for before God, but that other meanes likewise may lawfully, yea and for the most
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:197154:7"/> part ought to be used, for the obtaining therof. Woe be to Kings it this mans Doctrine should be received and practised home in the world. That insinuation of his p. 104. <hi>that a great part,</hi> (if not the greatest) <hi>of the Laws of this land, were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained little better then by force and violence, compelling Kings to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent unto them,</hi> being rightly interpreted, doth not so much reflect upon Parliaments (which yet was the good will and intent of the Insinuator) as upon Kings themselves, who (it seemes) could not be perswaded or drawn to yeeld to the establishing of good Lawes for their people, without little lesse then compulsion thereunto.</p>
               <p>I shall present you but with on threed more of this spinning, (for the present) which I draw out from p. 14. of his worthy piece: <hi>And in such (that is in a sinnefull] manner of assuming Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, there is just cause of resisting; and a faire colour of Rebelling against them, if you call it Rebellion, when men discharge their duties in defence of justice to oppose usurpation.</hi> Here is a blast of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine that were it put in practise, is enough to shake the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the Thrones and safeties of Most Kings now in possession; yea and to infringe and infeeble the right of their Posterities to their Crowns for ever. For how few Kings are there at this day sitting upon Thrones, some of whose Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, from whom they derive their rights and Titles, <hi>have not assumed their government in a sinfull manner?</hi> If such <hi>a manner of assuming their Governments</hi> did evacuate their Titles, and made them unlawfull Kings, and gave the subjects of that Kingdome <hi>just cause of resisting</hi> and de-throning them; Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they who succeed them in their Thrones, can have no better or more justifiable Title, then their Predecessors, from whom they derive their Title-hood; and therfore <hi>affirme their Governments in a sinnefull manner</hi> also: and consequently <hi>there is just cause of resisting them,</hi> and <hi>men did but discharge their duties in opposing such usurpation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly if the Fathers or Grandfathers right for never so many descents, was no better then an usurpation, and they, as usurpers, might lawfully have bin resisted; the right of the Son, being none other then what descends upon him from these, can be no better then an usurpation neither; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:197154:7"/> there is the same justice to resist and depose him; which was to have resisted his usurping progenitors One of your sinfull manners of assuming Governments, is when the assumer murthers his predecessor; another, when hee depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Did not WILLIAM Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> (sirnamed the Conquerer) murther King <hi>Harold,</hi> his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor in his Throne? except you will justifie one Prince in pulling out the throat of another and make all Wars between King and King lawfull. Now then by your divinity, <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> after hee had taken possession of his Crowne, might lawfully have bin resisted by the people, and they had but done their duties in defence of justice that had resisted him. You that have thus poysoned the fountaine, let the world judge how little the streames are beholding to you, you will never thrive by Hoggs, if you bring them to no fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Market then this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. II. <hi>The first Encounter of the Author of the</hi> Grand Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion <hi>against the</hi> Anti-cavalier, <hi>about that Scripture passage,</hi> 1 Pet 2. 13. <hi>Examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Philo-Cavalier takes no knowledge of his Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist, for the first 47 <hi>pages</hi> of his Pamphlet, and upwards, but at the last line of <hi>page</hi> 48. hee lay's on with his Crosiers staffe after this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And therefore though I doe not wonder that ignorant fellowes should be so impudent, as to affirme the King or Kingly Government to be the Ordinance or Creation, or Creature of man, and to say that the Apostle supposeth the same, because he saith, Submit your selves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords sake, whether it be unto the King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Yet I doe admire that</hi> Buchanan, <hi>or any other man of learning,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You may please to take notice, that the man was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:197154:8"/> well in breath and long-winded (halfe to a miracle) when he came here to grapple with his adversarie; for hee makes a period or sentence lasting two whole pages, and part of a third, between the rise of his sentence in his <hi>Quanvis,</hi> and the fall in his <hi>amen</hi> answering to it there are five dozen of lines (at least) full stuffed, partly with sense, partly with non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sense; as we shall see presently. This sentence (it seems) was built by him with like difficultie and badnesse of successe, as the City <hi>Iericho</hi> of old was built by <hi>Hiel,</hi> who <hi>layd the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof in</hi> Abiram <hi>his first borne, and set up the gates ehereof in his youngest Son</hi> Segub. 1 King. 16. 34.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> had neither silver nor gold, but gave the poore Cripple such as they had: So this man it seemes hath neither learning nor modesty, but such as he hath, hee gives his poore Brother <hi>Ignorance and Impudence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Sir, how ignorant I pray you, is the <hi>Anti-cavalier?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He is not so ignorant as contrary to all rules of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, and principles of Rhetorique, and the common and known Laws of speaking and discourse, to place severall whole periods of speech, betweene a <hi>Quamvis</hi> and a <hi>tamen,</hi> relating each to other, as in the same sentence.</p>
               <p>Nor yet 2. is he so Ignorant as to say, <hi>that the King is invested with the power of the people;</hi> and yet in the very same place to affirme, <hi>that the King is the fountaine of all power.</hi> This is your ignorance, <hi>pag.</hi> 65. of your discourse) not his. Surely if the power, wherewith the King is invested, was first in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the King is not the fountaine of all power.</p>
               <p>Nor 3. Is he so Ignorant as to say, <hi>that the people freed</hi> Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than <hi>out of the hand of Saul,</hi> non armis sed precibus, <hi>that is,</hi> not by force, but by prayers. This is a feather of your Goose, <hi>p.</hi> 55. not of his. <hi>And the people said unto</hi> Saul, <hi>shall</hi> Jonathan <hi>die, who hath wrought this great salvation in</hi> Israel? <hi>God for bid! as the Lord liveth, there shall not one haire of his head fall to the ground.</hi> 1 Sam. 14. 45. This surely is no Common Prayer, to sweare or protest before a King that that shall be done which a man hath a minde to have done. I see Bishops have little skill in Prayers but onely in those that are Common; which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly these of the peoples to <hi>Saul</hi> were not.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:197154:8"/>
               <p>Nor yet 4<seg rend="sup">o</seg> is he so ignorant, as to say, <hi>that the Ivie so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twisteth it selfe about the Oake, that the one cannot happily subsist without the other.</hi> This you say, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. of your Discourse: I cannot but wonder how you came to the knowledge of this profound secret in nature, that the Oake cannot subsist, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Ivie twisting it selfe about it. I do not remember it in <hi>Aristotles Problems,</hi> nor in <hi>Theophrastus</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But the comparison (I confesse) is very apt to represent the termes of relation between the two subjects you speake of, The Church you meane (which in your known Dialect, is the Praelaticall Clergie) and the Common wealth, have bin hitherto, and yet in part are so linked together, that as the Ivie intwisteth it selfe about the Oake, <hi>viz.</hi> to the sore detriment and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paireing and with perill to the life of it; so hath your Church circumvented and compassed about the estate and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, to the extreame misery and sorrow thereof and to the imminent danger of the very subsistence and being of it.</p>
               <p>Nor yet 5<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. is the man you wot of so ignorant, as to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that <hi>an unjust malicious Magistrate, hath this ordinary power from God, to lay punishment unjustly upon us,</hi> which yet your ignorance inableth you to affirme, <hi>p.</hi> 26. what you meane by an ordinary power in this case, I confesse I know not: but certaine I am, that to say that any Magistrate at all, whether just or unjust, whether gracious or malicious, hath any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at all from God, whether ordinary or extraordinary, <hi>to lay punishment unjustly vpon any man</hi> is as like the sound of an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tub as may be. And how much more to affirme, that <hi>our Saviour should</hi> say this unto <hi>Pilate?</hi> From which affirmation notwithstanding all your learning (it seems) was not able to deliver you.</p>
               <p>Nor 6<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. is he so ignorant, as to say, <hi>that hee that fighteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Kings army, warreth against the King,</hi> yet this you say, <hi>p.</hi> 97. which is, as if a man should say, that a Physitian that fighteth against the distemper or disease of his patient fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth against his Patient himselfe: Or that he that seeketh to rend and teare the Ivie from about the Oake, endeavoureth to annoy and hurt the Oake also. Neither will your paralell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance relieve you at all against the imputation of this absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:197154:9"/> except you can first prove by as sufficient testimony, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> is as much misused &amp; led aside to its own ruine and ruine of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> by the Earle of <hi>Essex</hi> as it hath bin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that the King is misused by his Army and Persons about him.</p>
               <p>Nor 7<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. is hee so ignorant as to deny, that either <hi>Joseph in swearing by the life of</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>or the Midwives in lying unto the King, sinned.</hi> But whether your ignorance teacheth you not to deny both, let the 56. <hi>p.</hi> Of your booke be asked the ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Nor 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. is he so ignorant, as to prove, that <hi>Kings are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by God himselfe to be of divine Institution, because hee calleth</hi> Nebuchadnezzar <hi>his servant, and</hi> Cyrus <hi>his annointed.</hi> This is your demonstration, <hi>p.</hi> 48. If every thing that God useth or disposeth of for the fullfilling of his pleasure and purposes in any kind, should presently bee of divine institution the rage and malice and murtherous spirit of the Jews against Christ, should be of Divine institution too: For these were made use of and disposed by him, to bring to passe a counsell and purpose of his of farre greater consequence both for his own glory, and for the benefit of his Church, then any thing that either <hi>Cyrus</hi> or <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> did see <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 7, 28. Kings may bee <hi>his Servants,</hi> and Monarchs <hi>his annointed ones</hi> though the institution of the kinds and formes of their governments, were from men. There is no man (I thinke) that ever thought or said, that those men, who whilst they were yet Subjects: were the servants and annointed of God, must necessarily forfeit these priviledges by being taken up into a Throne.</p>
               <p>Nor 9<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. (and lastly) is he so ignorant, as to say, that <hi>the rights and Prerogatives which are afforded the King by the Lawes of his owne Land come farre short of and are scrase the moitie of those Prerogatives, which the spirit of God hath in the</hi> Old Testament, <hi>warranted upon the Jewish Kings; and what the universall law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath established upon all Supreame Governors.</hi> Your Pen blotted your paper with these lines, in <hi>p.</hi> 104. of your Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course. <hi>I wonder what, or how many Prerogatives those should be, which the Spirit of God hath warranted unto the Jewish Kings in the Old Testament.</hi> It seemes they are like unto <hi>the Starres in the</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:197154:9"/>
                  <hi>Firmament of Heaven:</hi> the man can neither <hi>number them, nor call them by their Names.</hi> But why doth hee neither <hi>number nor Name,</hi> so much as any one of them? It may be he was afraid of an end of an old Saw.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pauperis est numerare pecus—</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'Tis poore Mans guise his Cattell 'ere to number.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>He conceives that he makes the better provision, to make them to bee had in reverence by men, both for their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and their glory, by wrapping both up in that mysterious silence which he hath done. The Inhabitants of <hi>terra incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita,</hi> are the goodliest men in the World. I doe not thinke that the man, notwithstanding his Censorian Rod layd on with so much severity upon the backe of ignorance, knowes any other <hi>Prerogatives warranted by the spirit of God unto the</hi> Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish <hi>Kings in the Old Testament,</hi> but onely these and the like. 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>That they should not multiply horses.</hi> 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>That they should not cause the people to returne unto</hi> Egypt. 3<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>That they should not mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply Wives to themselves, that their heart turne not away.</hi> 4<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>That they should not multiply to themselves silver and Gold.</hi> 5<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>That they</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 17 16 17, 18, 19, 20.</note>
                  <hi>should read the booke of the law of God all the dayes of their life.</hi> 6<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>That they should learne to feare the Lord their God, to keep all the words of his law to doe them.</hi> 7<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>That their heart should not bee lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up above their Brethren.</hi> 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. (and Lastly) <hi>that in case they tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not aside from the commandement either to the right hand or to the left, they should prolong their dayes in his Kingdome; they and their Children in the middest of Israel.</hi> If you will call these Prerogatives, I doe not know but the laws of the Land afford them all unto his Majestie in as ample manner, as you can desire them. As for other Prerogatives besides these, warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the spirit of God in the Old Testament to the Jewish Kings, I must be a debter to your informations, to attaine the knowledge of any: when you shall have fully informed mee, what, and how many they are, I shall bee the better able to give you an accompt, whether the laws of the land doe afford them unto his Majestie, or no; and whether those, which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:197154:10"/> these lawes doe afford him, bee not <hi>the mortie of them.</hi> In the meanetime I must, though at the perill of your displeasure, believe, that the laws of the Land doe afford unto him, and that in good measure, heaped up and running over all Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives whatsoever warranted by the spirit of <hi>God</hi> to the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish Kings, and which the universall Law of nature hath esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished upon all Supreame Governors. But</p>
               <p>By all these particulars, and many more like to them, that might be added it fully appeares, that the <hi>Anti-Cavalier</hi> hath not so monopoliz'd the commodity of ignorance, but that the Philo-Cavalier hath much of it lying upon his hand al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so. And the truth is, that notwithstanding by his severe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation against ignorance, he insinuats himselfe a choyce vessell of learning and knowledge: yet there are more then a few in the world, who know that farre the greatest part of a Bishops estate in learning, is ordinarily put into two bags; the treasure of the on being a heap of sayings and sentences gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the hand of an Index, out of authors, for the flattering of Princes: the treasure of the other, a like collection for the reparation and maintenance of the Episcopall Chayre. Take them out of these two Theames, they are (for the most part) like <hi>pisces in arido,</hi> quite out of their Element.</p>
               <p>And that this Bishop by name, makes treasure and very precious substance of such collections as we speak of is evident from hence; because he layes them up with that extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefullnesse and intensnesse of mind, wherewith covetous old men are wont to lay up their gold. Himselfe confesseth in his Epistle to the Reader, that when he composed his Grand Rebellion, he had not his bookes about him: which plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shewes, that those allegations and sentences from Authors, which are (almost) without end; (I am sure to no good end) heaped up in his Discourse, kept his heart company very neerely, and had double and treble care and cost bestowed upon them in their laying up. Otherwise, it is little lesse then an incredibility, that a man should carry such vast mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of other mens sayings <hi>verbatim</hi> in his head, except his heart were deep in the cōfedracy also. I do not believe that he remembers, or is able to say by rote, as much more; out of all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:197154:10"/> the Authors or bookes that ever he read. Therefore though he had not his bookes about him; yet he had the best part of his estate in learning about him, his Conn'd sentences for the undoeing of Kings.</p>
               <p>But 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. he is so advanced in choller against the Anti-Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, that hee is not satisfied with powring out the contempt of <hi>Ignorance</hi> upon him, but further to grind his name and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to powder; he arraignes him at the Barre of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory for the foule sinne of <hi>Impudence</hi> also. I see it's ill hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before a Cripple: (however;) the common saying is, set a Thiefe to take a Thiefe. The man it seemes is so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely well experienced in the point of impudence; that he is able to discerne it where it is not, yea where there is not the least colour nor appearance of it. For all that he charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him with to make good his sore inditement, is that hee affirmes, <hi>The King or Kingly government, to be the ordinance, cred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or creature of man: and, that the Apostle supposeth the same, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause be saith submit,</hi> &amp;c. All which amounts to no more, then to what himselfe granteth, and affirmeth immediatly, saying, <hi>that he</hi> (the Anti-Cavalier) <hi>might well understand</hi> (which I presume he very well doth) <hi>that the same act; is often ascribed as well to the mediate, as immediate agent. &amp;c.</hi> So then suppose man to be but the mediate agent in, or about; the Creation of Kingly Government (which himselfe here supposeth) and God the immediate, <hi>(cujus contrarium verum est)</hi> yet may this creation, by his owne rule be as well ascribed <hi>to man, the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, as to God the immediate Agent,</hi> So that the height of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; to make good both those hainous crimes, <hi>of ignorance and impudence,</hi> against the Anti Cavalier amounts to no more then this, that the Anti-Cavalier, hath no more learning or ingenuity in him, then to be of a Bishops judgement.</p>
               <p>But Sir, give me leave to tell you that if a man would be so ill minded towards you, as to charge you with impudence, your <hi>Grand Rebellion</hi> would in many passages of it justifie the accusation to your face. For,</p>
               <p>1<seg rend="sup">o</seg> doe you not <hi>p.</hi> 68. Fome out your owne shame in these words? <hi>It is well known to all the World, that whatsoever this good King hath suffered</hi> (speaking of His Majestie) <hi>at the hands of his</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:197154:11"/>
                  <hi>Subjects, it is for preserving the true</hi> Protestant Religion, <hi>of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablished lawes of this Kingdome,</hi> &amp;c. Surely you have a very lax, wide, and Cathedrall conscience, or else such a prodigious and shamelesse monster of untruth could never have bin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived there. If you had onely said, that it had bin suspected, or partly believed in the World, that <hi>the King hath suffered</hi> for those reasons you mention, it had bin a pretty streine of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, except you equivocate, and <hi>by the World,</hi> meane the World Malignant only. For in all the World besides, I know not the least touch of any suspition this way, but discover a full satisfaction to the contrary, on every hand. Nay in the Malignant World it selfe, I verily believe, that it is rather said and pretended then believed. But that which is not so much as thought, or suspected in the World, you strein cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie both with your conscience and your forehead at once, to affirme, that <hi>it is knowne,</hi> and that not simply <hi>to the World,</hi> but, <hi>to All the World;</hi> Nay, as if you were up upon your tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toe's to be <hi>aut Caesar, aut nullus,</hi> in point of impudence, you advance yet higher and say, <hi>that it is WELL KNOWNE to all the World.</hi> A man would thinke by such a deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Conscience and Pen as this is, that you had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken your solemne leave of modesty, shamefastnesse and truth, and never meant to see their faces, or to have to do with them more. And to make your Conscience leave muttering and lingering after them you seale up your resolution in this kind, with another egge of the same Bird, <hi>p.</hi> 105. towards the end of your Discourse, where you give one tumble more in the same mire, affirming <hi>that the King suffereth all for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Gods service, as it was established in the purest time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and for the preservation of our lawes from any corrupt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, or arbitrary invasion upon them,</hi> &amp;c. The man (questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onlesse) hath very lately (as if hee had quite forgotten his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions to the Virgin <hi>Mary)</hi> Sacrificed to the Goddesse <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and is now,</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—Functus que sacris, et potus, et exlex</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Full of his holy Sacrifice.</l>
                     <l>High drunken and of lawlesse guise.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:197154:11"/>
               <p>I wonder what Crotchet hath fallen in conjunction with the Rochet to inspire the man with any such notion or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that the <hi>King</hi> should <hi>suffer for the protection of Gods Service, or for the preservation of our laws from any corrupt interpretation,</hi> &amp;c. Doth hee not make himselfe greater then the Parliament it selfe, in taking upon him to know the reasons and motives upon which they have advanced the forces now on foot, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then themselves? Or have they ever declared any such ground of those proceedings of theirs, which (it seemes by this Counsellor of state) are troublesome unto the King or as he suggesteth. Surely he hath plowed with some malicious or mad Heifer, to make such an interpretation of so easie a rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. If the retinue of <hi>Jim</hi> and <hi>Ojim</hi> about his Majesties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, those hairy Apostates from humanity it selfe, be in the Bishops judgment, the service of God; well may he say, that <hi>the King suffers for the protection of the service of God.</hi> Or if the ruine and destruction of the Land by those walking sacks of blood, the Cavaliers, be the <hi>preservation of our laws from corrupt interpretation,</hi> it is somewhat a tolerable conjecture, to thinke the King may suffer for it. But if by the service of God he meanes either the truth of Religion, purity of his worship, or the like; and by preservation of the laws from corrupt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, any such thing as the knowne signification of the words import; hee might with farre lesse disparagement to himselfe in point of reason, wit, and honesty, have affirmed, that the King suffers for not making the Sun to shine, or the Winds to blow when the Parliament would have him.</p>
               <p>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. If that saying of yours, p. 29. <hi>viz. That a King hath power &amp; Authority to doe what he pleaseth,</hi> were presented to the Lady Modestie, I believe shee would blush at it, and not own it. Nor would any man that hath not his forehead fenc'd with Iron and Brasse, ever have adventured his reputation abroad in the world, in such a rotten bottome. Who ever gave a King pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authoritie to doe what he pleaseth, God, or Man, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be those enemies both of God and Man, I meane the Lords of the Chayre? <hi>Quod libet, licet,</hi> was an abhorring and hissing even amongst the Heathen.</p>
               <p>3<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. What fellowship, or communion, either with modeyst or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:197154:12"/> truth, hath that saying of yours, <hi>p.</hi> 101. <hi>that both the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment forces in England, and the Rebells in</hi> Ireland, <hi>make little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. betwene Papist and Protestant, the well affected and disaffected: and that the estates of both, is the thing that they thirst after?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet as if you had not been shamelesse enough in your affirmation, you seale it up, with this triumphant <hi>Epiphonema; Haud ignota Cano.</hi> I see how ever the World goes, yet Bishops will be merry and sing.</p>
               <p>I confesse the Parliament Forces, in the judgement of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, make too little difference in one respect, <hi>between Papist and Protestant; the well affected and disaffected;</hi> they shew more of the favour and forbearance, which they expresse towards the well affected, <hi>to Papists and disaffected,</hi> then their share comes to. But to thirst after the estates either of the one or of the other, is the disease that reigneth amongst your Legions: if there bee a sprinkling of it amongst the Parliament forces, I feare so much the more a Partie of yours amongst them. But (I see) it doth the man good at the heart, to make the Parliament forces in <hi>England;</hi> and Rebells in Ireland to draw in the same yoke of obloquy and reproach together.</p>
               <p>4<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Let Charity herself Judge, whether that be not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the highest, for a man that is himself a Bishop to call any proceedings in an assembly, especially in a Parlimentary assembly, against Bishops by the name of a Rebellion. And let the Reader iudge, whether you be not the man that speak at this rate, making your self, and all of your Order, Kings and Princes (at least) in these words of yours, <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any assembly hath (like</hi> Corah) <hi>rebelled against</hi> Aaron, <hi>and cast their Bishops and preachers out of doores: I would advise them to follow the Councell of S</hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">t</seg> Ambrose <hi>in the like case.</hi> Quod incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulto fecerunt, consultius revocetur; <hi>what they have inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately done to throw them out, let them more advisedly revoke, and call them in againe.</hi> It is an easie matter to discerne for what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian this Calculation is made; and what assembly it is, that is complained on for <hi>rebelling against Aaron,</hi> that is, for <hi>casting their Bishops and preachers out of doores.</hi> I tell you Sir, that all the water in the Sea will never wash you cleane from the guilt of impudence, who being but a single and simple man;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:197154:12"/> shall tell such an assembly as the Parliament of <hi>England: they have done any thing inconsideratly.</hi> Might not the malefactor when he is cast by the Judge at the Barre, with as much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty, tell the Judge that he knew the law better then he, and that he had given an uniust sentence? But to call that act of this great assembly, whereby they cast their Bishops (for Preachers I believe they cast out none) out of doores, <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> smell's so ranke of the Chayre, that it is enough to fill the whole Kingdome with the stench and ill savour of it; and to move every man to tread and trample upon the Chaire as a snuffe.</p>
               <p>In the meane time, these ejaculations from the Philo-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, with many more like unto them that bear them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in his booke, are sufficient to satisfie any reasonable man, that the Anti-Cavalier, is neither <hi>so ignorant, nor so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent,</hi> but that he hath his Peeres, yea and superiors too in both, and that amongst those Cherubims and Seraphims themselves, who would so faine recover their lost Heaven in PARLIAMENT.</p>
               <p>How sleight the ailement of the man is, to make these hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous outcries of ignorance and impudence against the Anti-Cavalier, was formerly touched: His grievement onely is, <hi>that he affirmes the King or Kingly Government to be the ordinance or creation of man, and that the Apostle supposeth the same.</hi> The man surely is besides himselfe, to fall so heavy upon another, for saying onely that which himselfe saith. In this expression of himselfe, the Anti-Cavalier determineth nothing either for or against any particular sence or consideration, in which the King or Kingly Government, may be called the creation of Man. And himself expressely, grants (not many lines af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) that there is a sence, which he call's <hi>secondary or demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, wherein the power and authority of Kings, is as S</hi>
                  <seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Peter <hi>calleth it, the ordinance of man.</hi> Hee that affirmeth <hi>Gregory,</hi> or <hi>Griffith Williams,</hi> (or whatever the name of the Hobgoblin, <hi>Gr.</hi> bee) to be an Irish Bishop, doth not deny him his Bishoprick of <hi>Ossory.</hi> Nor doth he that saith, he is worthy to bee punished for his Grand Rebellion, deny but that hee is worthy to lose his Priest-hood for it. Generall and indefinite sayings, do not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:197154:13"/> at all contradict particulars that are subordinate to them.</p>
               <p>Well, but though the Anti-Cavalier say nothing in this passage contrary to him, yet hee doth not speake out, as hee would have him; he is jealous of him that hee meanes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to him; and <hi>that when he affirmes Kingly Government to be the creation of man,</hi> his intent is, to exclude it from being the ordinance of God, at least from being the ordinance of God in the sence <hi>Paramount</hi> which hath bin consecrated by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Bishops. But,</p>
               <p>Might he not aswell fall foule upon S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> for speaking no otherwise then the Anti-Cavalier doth, as upon the Anti-Cavalier for speaking as S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Peter doth? St, <hi>Peter</hi> plainly sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth the <hi>King to be the creature or ordinance of man;</hi> but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he meanes <hi>primarily</hi> or <hi>secondarily,</hi> he expresseth himselfe no more then the other. But the man (its like) is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineable to have a good opinion of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <hi>Peter,</hi> and to befriend him in his thoughts, for the See of <hi>Romes</hi> sake, which claim's speciall interest in this Apostle, then he is of the Anti-Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, whose loyalty to that Chaire (I perceive) hee much suspects.</p>
               <p>But however it be somewhat an hard measure to be attaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as an <hi>ignorant and impudent fellow,</hi> onely upon suspition that a man will not conforme his judgement and conscience to a Bishops distinction; yet let the matter of fact bee confessed and acknowledged, and the Justice of it argued a little, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted upon.</p>
               <p>The difference then betweene the two combatants, as touching the point in hand, consists in these two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p>1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. The Bishop affirmes, that <hi>God was unto</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Saul, <hi>and is to all other Kings, the immediate giver of their Kingdomes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</hi> This the Anti-Cavalier deny's.</p>
               <p>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. The Bishop affirmes, <hi>the power and authority of Kings to be originally and primarily the ordinance of God.</hi> This his Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist craves leave to explaine (as he hath done, <hi>p.</hi> 5. &amp; 6. Of his Anti Cavalierisme) or else to deny.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:197154:13"/>
               <p>For the former; me thinkes that a very few words should serve to bring forth the truth into a cleere and perfect light between them. If <hi>God</hi> was <hi>the immediate giver of their Kingdoms, unto</hi> Saul <hi>and</hi> David, and the people <hi>the mediate,</hi> then the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were before God in the donation of them unto them, and God onely interven'd to second, ratifie and accomplish the donation of the people.</p>
               <p>Every freshman knowes, that the immediate agent or cause of any thing, is the last and lowest in the subordination; and that which produceth the effect without the intervention of any other: and that all the rest, that have precedency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, are mediate or remote. Therefore if God was the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate giver of <hi>Sauls</hi> or <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdome, and the people the mediate, the people made use of God and not God of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, actually to invest and inthrone them.</p>
               <p>Besides, evident it is, that Gods election, nomination, or recomendation of them to the people, for their Kings, did not make them Kings, I meane actuall, formall and compleat Kings; no, nor yet his inclining their hearts to a willingnesse to accept of them for their Kings, and to invest them with their power, but their actuall acceptation or receiving of them, for their Kings. <hi>Saul</hi> was not a King, that is, had no right or authority to exercise any Regall power by vertue of Gods election or nomination of him to the Kingdome, till <hi>Samuel</hi> had presented him unto all the people, as nominated by God to be their King, and the people gave their consent and approbation of him accordingly, in that acclamation, <hi>God save the King,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 24. The people in this their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of him for their King, were the immediate givers of the Kingdome unto him, because this being done, he had a lawfull power to exercise Regall authority over the people immediately, and without the intervening of any further act of God. Nor had <hi>David,</hi> though nominated and designed long before by God himselfe to the Kingdome; any right to exercise Regall power by vertue of that designation, untill <hi>the men of Judah came, and annointed him King in</hi> Hebron, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 4. Nor had he any right by vertue of his annointing, to exercise any Regall power over any other of the Tribes, save
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:197154:14"/> onely that Tribe which annointed him, and thereby declared their acceptation of him for their King. Hee was not King over all <hi>Israel,</hi> till all the Tribes came to him, and by their Elders anointed him King over Israell, therby declaring their consents and approbations to have him their King also. And now <hi>David</hi> was invested with Regall power and authority. So that the Sun in his might shines not clearer, then this truth, that God was not the immediate but onely the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate giver of their Kingdoms, both unto <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David.</hi> And though it had bin sinnefull in the People to have refused ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them for their King, being by Name, and by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery of a great Prophet recommended unto them by <hi>God</hi> yet had such a refusall bin made of them by the people, there is no reason to thinke that they had ever bin Kings. And therefore God himselfe divides betweene himselfe and his people the constitution of a King amongst them, after this manner; that he will have the choice or nomination of him, but they shall have the investiture, or the actuall and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate making of him a King. <hi>When thou art come into the Land which the Lord God giveth thee, and shalt possesse it, and shalt dwell therein, and shalt say; I will set a King over me, like as all the Nations that are about me: thou shalt in any wise set (or make, as the former translation reads it) him King over thee, whom the Lord thy God shall chuse: thou mayst not set a stranger over thee,</hi> &amp;c Deut. 17. 14. 15. Therefore God was onely the mediate or remote cause of their King, themselves the immediate: because election or nomination to an office, alwaies preced's, actuall collation of it.</p>
               <p>Hence likewise it fully appeares, how left handed the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop is in his understanding of Scriptures. To prove that <hi>God</hi> was the immediate giver of their Kingdomes to the two Kings mentioned, he cites such passages as these. <hi>Thus saith the Lord God of Israel</hi> (viz. to David) <hi>I anointed thee King over Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell,</hi> 2 Sam. 12. 7. and that of <hi>Solomon.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 24. Where he acknolwedgeth <hi>that the Lord had established him, and set him on the Throne of</hi> David <hi>his father;</hi> and that of <hi>Abijah</hi> to <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> 1 Kin. 11. 35. <hi>I will take the Kingdome out of his sons hand, and will give it unto thee.</hi> All which places onely prove, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:197154:14"/> all these Kings were beholding to God for their Kingdomes, and that he by his providence, working and inclining the hearts of the people to accept of them from his hand for their Kings, brought them unto their Thrones. Here is neither proofe, nor shew nor colour of proofe, of Gods being the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate giver of their Kingdomes. When God saith, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20. 25. <hi>that he gave them</hi> (the people) <hi>Statutes that were not good, and judgements wherein they should not live:</hi> doth it follow from hence, that God was the immediate giver of them? He was no otherwise the giver of them, then by suffering their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Kings and false Prophets to make and to teach Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Statutes and Doctrines amongst them. These were the immediate givers of these Statutes that were not good, <hi>Gene.</hi> 19. 29. God is said to <hi>have destroyed the Cities of the plaine:</hi> doth it follow from hence, that God was the immediate destroyer of them and did not use the ministerie or mediation of fire and brimstone to doe it? The Bishop is every whit as weak in his Theologicalls, as in his logicalls, if he knowes not that any event in providence may be attributed unto, or assumed by God, whatsoever and how many-soever the intermediate or immediate productive causes thereof be, because hee rules and orders and disposeth them all towards the production thereof.</p>
               <p>The latter difference between them touching the point in hand, is, whether the power and authority of Kings be <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and primarily</hi> the ordinance of God. This the Bishop af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes without any caution, or explication at all. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Cavalier must distinguish and explaine, or else deny. If the Bishops meaning be, either first, that God is the primary and Supreame disposer of thrones and Kingdomes, and that there is no man invested with regall power and authority, but that he is more indebted unto God, then unto any man, or men whatsoever, for it: or Secondly, if his meaning be, that <hi>God</hi> is the originall and prime mover of the hearts of a people, to set a King over them whensoever they doe it, being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise at liberty to erect what forme of Government amongst themselves they please. or Thirdly, if his meaning be, that God gives men the light of Reason, judgment and understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:197154:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:197154:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:197154:16"/> whereby they are able to contrive and shape out such a forme or tenor of Regall power or authority, that the use and <hi>administration</hi> of it may be commodious and beneficiall unto them, in all these three sences, the <hi>Anti Cavalier</hi> can shake <hi>hands</hi> with the Bishop, in his opinion, <hi>that the power and authority of Kings is orginally and primarily from God.</hi> But if his meaning be (as the whole tenor of his Discourse gives it to be) that <hi>God</hi> at first, immediately and by himselfe, without the interven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the reasons and wills of men, drew a particular plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme or modell of Regall government, power, or authority, which he hath imposed upon the World as an Ordinance, for all Nations, or for any Nation, to set up amongst them; in this sence the <hi>Anti-Cavalier</hi> bids defiance to the Bishops opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, maintaining <hi>the power and authority of Kings to be originally and primarily the Ordinance of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Reasons are these.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reas: </seg>1</label> 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Neither doe the Scriptures, nor any other Author, so much as mention any such draught or plat-forme of Regall Authority, composs'd immediately by God himselfe; much lesse doe they mention any imposition by <hi>God</hi> of any such plat-forme upon the World to be observed. Therefore it is either pure ignorance or impudence in the Bishop, to father any such opinion: As for his discovery <hi>of all the parts of regall power Synechdochically set down,</hi> by God. <hi>when immediately after the stood he ordained the revenging sword of blood shed and the slavish servitude of paternall derision,</hi> (p. 47.) it is a discovery of the same Calculation with his, who lately found a Sea and Land and woods and Rivers, and (upon the matter) another world in the Moone. Certainely it is as lawfull, and as agreeable to this Ordinance of God, that blood-shed should be aveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the sword of any other forme of government, as in that which is Regall, and by inferiour Magistrates, in case their Authority will extend unto it, as the authority of Judges doe, as by the King himselfe. If the man can acquit himself no better in stating the Episcopall function from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, then here he doth the Regall; (and I suspect his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficiencie paralell in both) he will leave me under a strong jealousie that he is <hi>a plant which</hi> Christs <hi>Heavenly Father never</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:197154:16"/>
                  <hi>planted,</hi> and consequently must ere long <hi>be plucked up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reas: </seg>2</label> 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. If Regall power and authority bee originally the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God (in the sence Episcopall) then every forme of Regall power, which swerves or varies from that patterne or platforme, which is the ordinance of God, must needs bee a corruption of an Ordinance of God, and consequently sinfull and unlawfull. The sequel of this Proposition is undeniable. Every ordinance of God hath a certaine, limited and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat nature, whereby it is distinguished, and may be known from all other things; and the substituting of any other thing in the name or place of an ordinance of <hi>God,</hi> is a sin, and that of a high nature.</p>
               <p>Therefore I assume.</p>
               <p>But every forme of Regall power, which swerves or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries from that pattern which is supposed to be the ordinance of <hi>God</hi> is not sinfull, or unlawfull. <hi>Ergo;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the explication of this latter Proposition, it is to bee considered, that there are scarce any two forms of Regall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in exercise at this day in the world, but differ, and that in matters of such consequence, that if the one bee the Ordinance of God, the other is a corruption of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and so unlawfull. I suppose there is no such Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or power in any Nation, but is somewaies limited and bounded either by lawes, or customes, or covenants, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, or the like: and very hard it is, nay (doubtlesse) unpos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to find two Regall Governments in all the world, whose frame and fashion, whose bars and limitations are altogether the same. Whence it must needs follow, that if there bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such forme of Government, whether Regall or whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that is an ordinance of God, (in the sense now argued) there can be but one, if there be any at all, lawfull govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the world. For all governments differing from that, which is agreeable to the Ordinance of God are corruptions thereof, and so unlawfull. So then, till the Bishop can find out that Regall government in the world, which is the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of <hi>God,</hi> by his divinity all governments by <hi>Kings</hi> must bee questionable; and when that one is found out. all the rest besides, are evicted therby to be unlawfull. And thus we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:197154:17"/> see the truth of that saying, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27. 14. fullfilled in this mans importune standing up to make Kings greater then <hi>God</hi> hath made them; <hi>Hee that blesseth his friend with a loud voice, rising earely in the morning, it shall be counted a curse to him.</hi> His opinion of Kingly power and authority, being originally and primarily the ordinance of God, being interpreted is enough to make the Crownes of all the Kings upon earth, to droope and languish, and sit loose upon their heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj: </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>It is like, that he will lay hold of this shield and buckler, to save the life of his opinion, if it may be, Kings were originally ordained and appointed by God to rule: and this is sufficient to prove Kingly rule or Government to be originally and primarily the Ordinance of GOD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ: </seg>1</label> To this I Answer, first, It can never bee proved that Kings were originally ordained by God to rule. The first we read of, that assumed Regall power, was <hi>Nimrod, Gen,</hi> 10. 8. of whom it is said, <hi>that he began to bee a mightie one in the Earth;</hi> and his Kingdome is spoken of, <hi>vers.</hi> 10. There is not the least mention made, nor intimation given, that God had any thing to doe with the advancement of him to his Kingdome, by any ordinance or command of his; either to himselfe to rule as a King, or to the people overwhom hee Reigned, to receive him, or subject themselves unto him, as a King. Nor is their any colour to thinke, that either hee should have sin'd against any ordinance of God, in case hee had not made himself a King, or, that the people should have sin'd any such sin, in case they had not received him. It is true, God in a way of a generall and permissive providence, so disposeth of the pride and ambition of <hi>Nimrod's</hi> heart on the one hand, and of the weakenesse and ignorance of the people one the other, that betweene them both, <hi>Nimrod</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a King. But had Kingly rule or government bin an ordinance of God, doubtlesse he would never have lay'd the foundation of it in such a Tyrant and oppressor as he was. He should never have hansel'd such a solemn and sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of GOD as this is pretended to be. The next King heard of in the Scriptures, is <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Gen. 12. 15. and afterward Chap. 14. we heare of Kings by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:197154:17"/> heaps, foure making warre against five, and five against foure: but that any of these were put into their Kingdomes by God (otherwise then in a way of permissive and disposive providence, as was said) or by any ordinance of his, is as cleare as the heavens are to us in the darkest night. But</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ: </seg>2</label> Secondly, suppose it could be never so substantially prov'd, that men were at first ordayned and appointed by God (in the sence Episcopall) to take Kingly rule upon them, yet except it can be as substantially proved, what the nature, purport, extent, and limits of that rule or power which they exercised by vertue or warrant of that ordinance of God, were, there is nothing gotten by this, to justifie any Regall power now in exercise in the world. Though we could prove never so sufficiently, that Christ or his Apostles ordayned Pastors and Teachers in the Church to preach the Gospell, yet except we both knew what this Gospell was which they were ordayned to preach, and what this preaching it selfe was, the proofe of that Ordination by Christ and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, would not prove the Pastors and Teachers amongst us ever to have bin ordayned by them. Communion in Name between a present practise, and a practise ordayned by God, is a ridiculous foundation in reason, to prove the present practise to have bin ordayned by God. Therfore the Bishops opinion, that the Kingly Government which is now admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrd in the world, is originally the ordinance of God, will starve, notwithstanding this reliefe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reas: </seg>3</label> Thirdly, That Government or power which God never imposed upon any people under heaven to erect or set up amongst them, is not like to be the ordinance of God, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of observation to persons whom it concernes, being an essentiall adjunct of an ordinance of God. But God never imposed the government of Kings upon any Nation, but hath left all Nations free to erect amongst themselves what government they please, whether <hi>Aristocraticall, Democrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> and however mixt, so it be just and lawfull, as well as Regall. Therfore government Regall (in the sence Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall) is not the ordinance of God. The latter Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> That God hath left all Nations free to set what
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:197154:18"/> Government themselves please; over them, and consequently hath not imposed upon them that which is Regall, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from his owne grounds, who <hi>p.</hi> 48 affirmeth God to be <hi>the allower and confirmer of Aristocraticall and all other forms of Government.</hi> From whence I thus reason: If God bee the Allower and confirmer of all other formes of government, as well as of Regall, then were all Nations at liberty to set up any other forme of government, as well as it; for a man is at liberty to doe any thing, which God will allow and confirme when he hath done it: yea it is no whit lesse then blasphemy, to make God the <hi>Allower</hi> of what is sinfull or unlawfull to be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reas: </seg>4</label> 4<seg rend="sup">o</seg> If Government Regall be no otherwise from <hi>God,</hi> or no otherwise an ordinance of <hi>God,</hi> then inferiour Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and power is, then is it not originally and primarily from <hi>God. Sed verum prius; Ergo et posterius.</hi> The sequel in the Proposition is strong, as well, <hi>quoadrem</hi> as <hi>quoad hominem: quoadrem,</hi> because inferiour Magistracy, is both confer'd and given, and likewise limited and specified by men, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Soveraign power of the King himself as in such Officers and Magistrates, as his lawfull Prerogative gives him right and power to create: or else by the people, as in those Magistrates whose nomination and investiture either by law or priviledge of lawfull custome, belongs unto them: <hi>Quoad hominem;</hi> because he holds, that all inferiour Magis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracy or power, is of a farre inferiour descent and origina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in comparison of that which is Regall. And that it is wholly dependent upon this <hi>page</hi> 47, 65, 66. The truth of the assumption or antecedent, <hi>viz:</hi> that government Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall is no otherwise from God, then inferiour Magistracy or government is, is evident.</p>
               <p>1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Because this is said to be <hi>from Heaven,</hi> and to be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, as well as that: The Scripture makes no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or distinction, betweene the descent of the one and of the other, in this respect. Himselfe taketh notice <hi>(p.</hi> 47.) that Christ doth <hi>positively</hi> affirme <hi>that the power of Pilate was given him from Heaven;</hi> Which is indeed expresly so affirmed by him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 11. excepting only that the Bishop paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:197154:18"/> our Saviours <hi>from above,</hi> with his, <hi>from Heaven:</hi> For which though I cannot commend him, yet shall it bee no part of my contention with him at this time. Now <hi>Pilate</hi> all men know, had no Soveraigne or regall power, but was a subordinate magistrate, deputed to his place of government and rule by the Romane Emperour, and might at pleasure have bin removed by him. So againe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. it is said of <hi>all powers (viz.</hi> in rule and government) without any distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that they <hi>are ordained of God:</hi> and that there is no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (that is, no lawfull power whatsoever) but is <hi>of God: For there is no power but of</hi> God, <hi>the powers that bee</hi> (whether Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, or subordinate) <hi>are ordained of God.</hi> Againe,</p>
               <p>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. There is the same subjection, or subjection upon the same terms, charged upon the consciences of men, to the one authority, which is unto the other. <hi>Submit your selves to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ordinance of man for the Lords sake, whether it bee to the King as Supreame, or unto Governors, as unto them that are sent by him,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 14. Therefore there is no ground in Scripture, to conceive any other manner or kind of the issuing or descent of the Regall power from <hi>God,</hi> then is of the subordinate. All the difference which reason can demonstrate in this kind, is onely this; that the disposall of the hearts of people, and of other circumstances therewith concurring, to bring a King to a Throne, or Soveraignty of rule and power, is ordinarily a farre greater and more considerable act of divine providence; either for the benefit or bane of a people, then the moving of the heart of the King, or the disposing of other interveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, for the bringing of a man to an inferiour place of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy or power. But this is rather a difference in degree, then in kind</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reas: </seg>5</label> 5<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. If Regall government be the ordinance of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Ossorian</hi> glosse and interpretation, then cannot the desire or request of a Nation or people to have this go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment over them be called a <hi>rejecting of</hi> God <hi>from Raigning or ruling over them.</hi> But this desire or request made by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Jewes is by God himselfe interpreted, <hi>a rejecting or casting of him away, that he should not raigne over them,</hi> 1 Sam. 8. 67. Therefore certainely the Bishop of OSSORY is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:197154:19"/>
                  <hi>Clericus absque libro, nec valet ova duo;</hi> in his notion of Regall government being the ordinance of God. The assumption comes from the mouth of God, almost, and as good as, <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,</hi> let the Bishop deny it at his perill. And for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, the very sound of it is such and so distinct in the eare of reason, that a reasonable man cannot lightly but prepare his assent unto it immediately. For can any thing lightly be supposed more unreasonable, then that <hi>God</hi> should challenge and charge a people with a rejection of him, and his rule over them, onely because they desire such a rule or forme of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment amongst them, which is an ordinance of his after a more speciall and excellent manner, then any other?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason </seg>6</label> 6. That rule of Government, the non-exercise or non-use whereof throughout the whole World, would not have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred any man sinnefull or displeasing unto God, is not such a divine and supertranscendent ordiance of God above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther formes of Rule and government, as the Ossorian Oracle reports it to be. I remember I have to do with men so unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanoble, that if such a saying as this that <hi>twice two make foure;</hi> should make against them they are ready to cry out of the <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> and <hi>impudence</hi> of him that should affirme it: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the Proposition laid downe, hath a consistence with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and truth, manifest enough. But now, to bind the tongue of perversenesse to her good behaviour, take this String or Cord, that it no wayes suites with the glory of the wisdome of God; to set his seale of speciall excellencie upon any ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his and then to leave all the World at liberty, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will use it, or obey it or no. Therefore let mee now assume.</p>
               <p>But the non-exercise, or non-use of Kingly government, had the world generally ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d never to have used or imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the World, nor any member <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ent from what hath bin already ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> no Nation but might lawfully have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> government, as well as this (which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>) evident it is, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their refusing of this government had bin no wayes sinnefull. If the Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:197154:19"/> or use of the Regall government had bin necessary in point of duty, or had the government it self bin such a choice and divine Ordinance above all other governments, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse God would have imposed it upon his owne people, the Nation of the Jewes, though he had left others to their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But that he no wayes so much as recommended it unto them, but left them purely to themselves, whether they would set up a King over them or no; is every whit as much as fully evident, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 14. <hi>When thou art come to the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, and shalt possesse it and shalt dwell therein, and shalt say I will set a King over me like as all the Nations that are about me, thou shalt in any wise set him King over thee, whom the Lord thy God shall chuse,</hi> &amp;c. God doth not here say, that when they came into their Land, <hi>he would set a King over them</hi> or <hi>have them to set a King over them;</hi> but onely that in case they should <hi>say that they would set up a King over them;</hi> that is should freely and voluntarily desire or resolve upon such a govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that then for the person of him that should bee their King, he would have the election or nomination of him.</p>
               <p>Wee know that God himselfe had setled them under an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther government, <hi>viz:</hi> by Judges, wherein he had blessed and prospered them many yeers: and though it was not simply unlawfull for them to desire a King to beset over them (as appeares from the place in <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> last cited) yet this desire of theirs proceeding out of a dislike or discontentment at that government which God himselfe had set over them, or out of a superstitious conceipt of some divine excellency or perfection in the government they desired, above that which already they injoyed, was on high breach betweene him and them.</p>
               <p>If it bee lawfull to speake the truth withall simplicity and ingenuitie, I professe I never yet met with any sollid, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing argument, either from Scripture or otherwise, to prove that Regall government or power is in any other sense or consideration the ordinance of God, then in those three formerly expressed.</p>
               <p>As for those Scriptures, <hi>by me Kings Reigne,</hi> &amp;c. Prov. 8. 15. and again, <hi>There is no power, but of God: the powers that bee, are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:197154:20"/>
                  <hi>of God,</hi> Rom. 13. 1. with others of like consideration, they determine nothing in way of any speciall modification, as how, or in what sense whether <hi>originally and primarily, or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily, or demonstratively,</hi> onely <hi>whether mediately or immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> either Kingly power, or any other be ordained by GOD: much lesse doe they conclude any thing by way of Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for the manner of the issuing of Kingly power from <hi>God</hi> above any other All that they prove is that Kingly govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and power, as well as any other, are simply from God, and are ordained, or rather ordered (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) by God; which is a conclusion, wherewith the Anti-Cavalier is ready to fill the Bishops bosome with both his hands. As for those Episcopall modifications and explications of this conclusion which have bin argued, we have seen nothing liker the chaffe before the wind, then they.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. III. <hi>Wherein the</hi> Bishops <hi>second encounter against the</hi> Anti-Cavalier, <hi>about the carriage of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> Elisha, <hi>towards him that was sent to take away his head,</hi> 2 King. 6. 32 <hi>Is examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVHen</hi> Herod <hi>had killed</hi> James <hi>the brother of</hi> John <hi>with the sword,</hi> the text saith, <hi>that because he saw that it pleased the people, he proceeded further to take Peter also,</hi> Act. 12. 2, 3. The Bishop (it seems) hath either so pleased himself or his friends, with confuting the Anti-Cavalier (over the shoulder) once, that he proceeds to a like confutation of him the second time. The Anti-Cavalier pleads the practise and example of the Prophet <hi>Elisha,</hi> who caused <hi>the doore to be shut,</hi> and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, that was sent to <hi>take away his head, to be roughly handled,</hi> for lawfullnesse of resistance, against unlawfull executioners of unlawfull commands. That quarter in this discourse,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:197154:20"/> which the Philo-Cavalier falls upon, is this: <hi>surely hee that went thus farre</hi> (viz: as to cause the doore to bee shut, and the messenger of blood to bee roughly handled without) <hi>for the safety of his life, when he was but in danger of being assaulted, would have gone further if occasion had bin: and in case the Kings Butcher had got into him, before the doore had bin shut, if he had bin able, and had had no other meanes to have saved his owne head, but by taking away the others; there is little question to be made, but he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have taken, then given an head, in this case.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Against this, the Bishop advanceth with this answer (such as it is) that <hi>who this</hi> GOODWIN <hi>is, he knowes not: but he could wish, he were none of the Tribe of</hi> Levi, 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>Because he finds him such an incendiary of Warre,</hi> &amp;c. 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
                  <hi>because his objection is full of falsehoods, and false grounds,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If a man could answer objections, either with ignorance, or with a wish, I see there is no man like to a Bishop to cope with an adversary. For the forlorne hope or first advance of his answer, is, that <hi>hee knowes not who this</hi> Goodwin <hi>is,</hi> that set's the Prophet Elisha thus upon his back to vexe him. But doth not the man deny himself deeply, thus ingenuously to confesse his ignorance? No doubtlesse; it is very rare to find a Bishop under this Fig-tree. The designe of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession rather seemes to bee to indigitate his adversary as a <hi>filius terrae,</hi> and contemptible and obscure person, and himself brother to the Sun and Moone, a man of renowne. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the lamb had no great cause to be sorry if the wolfe knew her not. Nor hath <hi>this Goodwin</hi> any cause to bee troubled, that these great overseers overlooke him: he hath bin known to some of them to his cost. But though this son of the morning knowes not <hi>this Goodwin</hi> (that <hi>Ignorant</hi> and <hi>impudent</hi> fellow he spake of before) yet he knows Master <hi>Griffith</hi> to be a <hi>learned Divine,</hi> p. 94. and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Warmstry</hi> to be a <hi>learned preacher of Gods word,</hi> pag 32. both of them (I believe) <hi>men</hi> as much unknowne to him, as <hi>this Goodwin,</hi> excepting onely the relation of co-Malignancy or con-tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing between them.</p>
               <p>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. In the next place comes on the Vanne of his Answer, which is a wish, yet of no great strength neither, but a kind
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:197154:21"/> of velleitie: hee could wish that <hi>this GOODWIN were none of the Tribe of Levi.</hi> It is no strange thing for a Bishop to wish evill unto men: they have <hi>both the will and the deed,</hi> (in this kind) given unto them. I believe <hi>he could wish</hi> not onely that <hi>this GOODWIN,</hi> but that all the Ministers within the three Kingdomes, that are faithfull and through-hearted in the worke of the Gospel, were none <hi>of the Tribe of Levi;</hi> nor (I feare) of any other Tribe, but of that which is not.</p>
               <p>But it may bee the crookednesse of his wish, may bee made straight by the reasons and grounds of it. Let these therfore stand forth, and plead for their master.</p>
               <p>The first is, <hi>because he finds him such an incendiary of warre, and enemy unto peace. Such an incendtary? such an enemie?</hi> I pray as who? as your selfe, and men of your Order? Or as St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the rest of his Order? If he be such an incendiary of war, or enemy to peace as you and yours, let him smart for it: he deserves it. I shall never open my mouth, nor stirre my pen for him. For you annimate and exhort, and egge on all that have no more conscience then to hearken to you, to strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the hand of those that are risen up against that Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Assembly, the supreme Judicatorie or Court of Justice in the Land, and in them against the peace and safety of all his Majesties 3 Kingdomes; you (I say) stirre up all you can with both your hands to asiist and strengthen these men in their way, <hi>to the utmost of their power, by not sparing their goods, nor being niggards in their contributions:</hi> nay, you blow these coales yet hotter, and thrust them forward in this despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate service, <hi>even to the hazard and losse both of libertie and life,</hi> (pag. 105, 106. of your Discourse.) It is true, you baite your hook with the glossie pretence of His Majesties <hi>safety and protection,</hi> as if you call'd in all this helpe and assistance only for these: but your reall intentions are so notorious, and so strong above ground, that you gaine nothing by all your flourishes and pretences in this kind, but the deserved reproach of base hypocrasie and dissimulation on the one hand, and of being the generation of him that is called the <hi>accuser of the Brethren,</hi> one the other. For by your importune
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:197154:21"/> crying out for ayd and assistance to be brought in, for the safety and protection of his Majesty, you plainly insinuate, that it is the Parliament and those faithfull and loyall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his that stand by them for their defence and safety, that indanger his Majesty, and seek his life, Crown, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities: which is an accusation and charge of that desperate falshood and malice, that <hi>the Accuser of the Brethren</hi> we speake of, seemes to have given you <hi>his power and his Throne,</hi> as being more able to manage them for his advantage, then himselfe. This is to be <hi>an incendiary of warre, and an enemy to peace,</hi> to seek to disturbe, and to oppose the proceedings of Law and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice throughout the Land, to endeavour to strengthen the hand of malefactors and delinquents, that they may be able to wage warre against their lawfull and righteous Judges, to incence the people against those Rulers and Magistrates of theirs, who with upright hearts and unwearied endeavours, seeke the things of their peace and welfare, against those that have already more then begun to devoure them and are upon terms of advantage enough to finish their worke, and to make an utter end of them, if the people themselves will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded to joyne with them, and to help them, as you would have them.</p>
               <p>In this sence therfore, evident it is, that the Philo-Cavalier, not the Anti-Cavalier, is <hi>the Incendiary of warre, and enemie to peace.</hi> But in what sence, I pray will the accusation hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Anti-Cavalier? How is he <hi>an incendiary of warre?</hi> He exhorts and perswades people all he can, to keep their late vow and Protestation made unto God (not disallowed that ever I heard by his Majesty himselfe) as <hi>viz. to maintaine and defend, as farre as lawfully they may, with their lives, power, and estates, the true Reformed Protestant Religion; his Majesties Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all person, honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> estate the power and Priviledges of Parliament; the lawfull Rights and Liberties of the Subject, and every person that should make the same protestation in whatsoever he should doe in the lawfull persuance of the same. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o their power, and as farre as lawfully they may, to oppose, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> good wayes and meanes endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring to condig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> punishment, all such as shall either by force, practise, counsells, plots, conspiracie or otherwise, doe any thing to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:197154:22"/> contrarie of any thing in the said protestation contained: And neither for feare, hope, nor other respect, to relinquish this promise, vow and protestation.</hi> If the Anti-Cavalier hath moved little or much out of this his sphere let the Bishop beare testimony against him and upon due proof made, <hi>Satiet se sanguine, quem semper si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivit:</hi> let the Anti-Cavalier be sacrificed upon the service of his Anti-Christian and bloody spirit as <hi>an incendiarie of warre, and enemy to peace:</hi> but in the mean time (which I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion will be long enough) let the saddle be set upon the right Horse, and he that cryes out against the thiefe, be laid hold of for the thief himselfe.</p>
               <p>The second reason why he wishes <hi>this Goodwin</hi> out of his <hi>Tribe of Levi,</hi> is, <hi>because his objections is full of falshoods and false grounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But good Sir, this is an hard case, to wish a man unprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, because he makes an objection, with falsehoods and false grounds in it. If you ever have beene at the Universitie, or know any thing of the disputations there, you cannot but know, that Objections generally are <hi>falsholds, and built upon false grounds;</hi> yea and that, in case the respondent undertakes to defend the truth (which is presumed he alwayes doth; at least as farre as his judgement leadeth him) unpossible it is that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny disputation should be maintained, but onely by Obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Arguments that are falshoods, it being unpossible to oppose truth with truth. But I can easily excuse the man, though hee hath forgotten the use and signification of his termes in Logique, calling that an objection which is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: These were but the Nuts of his Boy-hood and youth. A great States-man, that hath his part and share of the burthen of two or three great Kingdoms upon his shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and all these in a grievous combustion, uprore, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion; is he at all to be blam'd, if he neglects the punctill'os and formalities of his Logique and hath no leisure to aske his wits the question, how Sophisters speake in the Schooles.</p>
               <p>In the head of his charge, he learnedly distinguisheth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>falshoods and false ground;</hi> but in making good his charge by insisting upon particulars, he confounds them again, as he doth himselfe. Well, but what are <hi>the falshoods or false grounds</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:197154:22"/> (call them what you will) wherewith the Anti-Cavaliers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, or argument (call it what you will, <hi>Bishops</hi> are for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty) is so full?</p>
               <p>Now to the heat and strength of the battell. His first charge is, that the Anti-Cavalier saith in his Objection, that <hi>Ahab sent to take Elisha's head, whereas</hi> Ahab <hi>was dead long before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I answer, 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. that the Bishop (it seemes) hath lighted upon a mis-printed Copy, wherein he met with the Father instead of the Sonne. A man would think that it were his hard hap, to light upon <hi>Bibles</hi> much mis-printed also, his opinions in divinity, being so dissenting from all Hagiographie of a true impression.</p>
               <p>But 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Whereas he saith, that <hi>Ahab was dead long before;</hi> I demand of him, as hee doth of the <hi>Anti-Cavalier</hi> a few lines after (in another case) <hi>what inspiration hee hath from God to bee sure of this?</hi> The Scripture determineth nothing of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, betweene <hi>Ahabs</hi> death, and this fact of his Sonne <hi>Iehoram.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But he goeth on and courteously granteth, <hi>that the Prophet, in his judgement, desiring the Elders to handle the messenger roughly; or hold him fast at the doore, did herein a little more, then what God and nature alloweth every man to doe, not to lay down his life, if he can lawfully preserve it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Where is to be noted, that though hee doth not cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Prophet <hi>Elisha</hi> for shutting the doore, as hee doth against the <hi>Anti-Cavalier,</hi> nor against Christ, for giving leave, <hi>when we are persecuted in one City, to fly into another,</hi> yet <hi>in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the doing of the one and of the other, was A LITTLE MORE <hi>then what God and nature allowed every man to do?</hi> It is no marveile if hee makes himself so much wiser then his poore Brethren whom he look's upon as so many Ignaro's, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sults over their ignorance with his knowledge, when as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets themselves, yea and the Lord of Prophets himselfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weighed in his ballance, have much adoe to (nay do not fully) hold out with his weights.</p>
               <p>But <hi>in all this</hi> which the Prophet did, hee tells us, <hi>that hee finds no violent resistance,</hi> What? and yet <hi>somewhat more then</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:197154:23"/>
                  <hi>what God and nature, alloweth every man to doe?</hi> Well, but yet he is here somewhat ingenuous and tender: he doth not abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deny, but that here might be some <hi>violent resistance;</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he professeth that he <hi>finds none.</hi> Juglers can hide and find at pleasure. The man (I believe) hath learned his <hi>Terence: Si sapis, quod scis, nescis:</hi> and his <hi>Cato</hi> too, who teacheth him that principle of policy, which here he makes use of.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Stultitiam simulare loco prudentia summa est,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg> i. e.
<lg>
                     <l>'Tis wisedom's highest strain, as time and place may be.</l>
                     <l>Wiselesse to make thy self, and nothing for to see.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>If His Majestie should come to demand entrance into any of the walled Cities of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> and those within should shut the gates against him, and not suffer him to enter, and withall <hi>should handle him roughly at the Gates:</hi> I believe the mans eyes would now bee opened, and hee would find <hi>violent resistance</hi> here. If by <hi>violent resistance</hi> he means, laying on dry blowes with a weapon, or cleaving a mans head in sunder with a Skaine or battell-Axe: I confesse that neither doe I (in this sense) find any <hi>violent resistance.</hi> But if by violent resistance, he meanes a strong and forcible opposition, a withstanding an assailant to the utmost of a mans power, at least to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of what was necessary to prevent the mischief that was intended against him, doubtlesse a <hi>violent resistance</hi> is easie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bee found in the Prophets carriage in this place. Nor did the Anti-Cavalier ever intend a legitimation of any further resistance by way of violence or force, then onely to such a degree, which may in prudence be thought fully suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to stave off the violence and iniustice of those, who without any lawfull authority shall advance against them. His meaning never was, to make it lawfull to draw a sword, when the shutting of a doore may be a sufficient security.</p>
               <p>But the words of the Bishops greatest indignation, against the Anti-Cavalier in this passage, are these: <hi>Surely if the messenger had got in,</hi> Elisha <hi>had taken of his head, rather then giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his owne.</hi> Here he demands, <hi>what inspiration the Anti-Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:197154:23"/>
                  <hi>hath from God to be sure of this?</hi> Withall affirming, <hi>that hee was sure that</hi> John Baptist <hi>would not doe so, nor St.</hi> Paul, <hi>nor any other of Gods Saints that he had read of: but these men are sure of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing, even of Gods secret counsell, and that is more then the thoughts of mens hearts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I answer, 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. I shall pardon the Bishops mangling and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailing the Anti-Cavaliers words for his owne advantage in this place, because hee had done honestly in a iust report of them before, whither the Reader may please to repaire for a full view of them. But</p>
               <p>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Whereas he demands, <hi>by what inspiration from God,</hi> his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagonist <hi>was sure of this?</hi> I answer, by a farre better inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then the Bishop had, either to affirme, <hi>that the Christians that were at Ierusalem when</hi> James <hi>was martyred, were more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and greater in power, then were the persecutors of that Apostle,</hi> which yet hee makes no bones to avouch, <hi>p.</hi> 21. or to say, <hi>p.</hi> 56. <hi>that neither</hi> Joseph <hi>in swearing by the life of</hi> Pharoah, <hi>nor the midwives in lying to the King, sinned:</hi> or then hee had to say, <hi>p.</hi> 68. that <hi>whatsoever the King hath suffered, all the world knowes it is for the preservation of the Protestant Religion, of the established lawes of this Kingdome,</hi> &amp;c. I marvaile, first; by what inspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all the world should know it. And I marveile yet more, by what inspiration the Bishop should know that all the World knowes it. And I would gladly know by what inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from God, he Prophesies and forsees, <hi>p.</hi> 68. that <hi>those Reverend Bishops, grave Doctors, and all the rest of the Learned and Religious Clergie, for whose preservation</hi> (as hee; like himselfe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth) <hi>the King suffers, will to the spilling of the last drop of their blood, defend the truth</hi> (I thinke he meanes of Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or that the King suffers all for the preservation of this Religion, &amp;c.) <hi>Against all Papists, and other Anabaptisticall Brownists and Sectaries whatsoever.</hi> Surely to determine and prophesie what himselfe would doe in such a case as hee here speakes of, requires no lesse then the knowledge <hi>of Gods secret Counsell.</hi> For 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. the man by his owne strength, and without speciall assistance from God, is not able to defend any truth of God, to the spilling of the first, much lesse to the spilling of the last drop of his blood; as wee see in the example of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:197154:24"/>
                  <hi>Peter,</hi> another manner of man to defend the truth with his blood, then the Bishop is (no dispraise to him) And 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>God</hi> will assist any man, much more a colloguing Bishop, so farre, when it comes to the tryall, as to defend a truth to the last drop of his blood, is not revealed, and therfore must needs be <hi>the secret counsell of God.</hi> But to undertake, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; I know not how many more, even <hi>all the learned and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Clergie,</hi> shall doe it, requires a greater inspiration in the kind, then ever Prophet Apostle, or Evangelist had. Yet let me advise a little better upon the Bishops expression, in that word, <hi>Religious:</hi> It may bee I may have cause to correct my selfe (in part) in what I have said. If his meaning be that <hi>all the Religious Bishops, Doctors and Clergie, for whose preservation his Majestie so suffers, will to the spilling of the last drop of their blood, defend the truth of Religion:</hi> I confesse this may be very reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably (as touching the truth of it) and in a way of good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability affirmed, without any extraordinary inspiration from God. For this is but a saying of like notion with this; that all the Fishes in the Sea, that are foules in the aire, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to fly: or this, all the Lambs in the Fold, that are Lyons in the Forrest, will bee able enough to deale with the Wolfe, when hee comes. Both these are truths manifest enough, though but simple ones.</p>
               <p>In such a figure and Character of speech as this, <hi>all the Bish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops, Doctors, and Clergie (for whose preservation the King suffers)</hi> that are Religious, may well defend the truth of Religion, <hi>to the spilling of the last drop of their blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to give the Bishop an accompt, by what inspiration from God, the Anti Cavalier affirmeth, that <hi>the prophet in case he had had no other meanes to escape, and had bin able, would rather have taken, then given, an head:</hi> he might very well, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of what the Prophet had done, speake this by the <hi>inspiration</hi> of reason, and (almost) of common-sence. For it is very reasonable to thinke and say, that hee that goes one mile to save his life, will goe two, if hee bee able; and there be no other meanes wherby to save it, The Prophet (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse) did more, more I meane in a geometricall or rationall proportion, in causing the Butcher to bee roughly handled,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:197154:24"/> and the doore to be shut against him, whilst hee was yet at such a distance from doing him harme, then hee should have done in taking away his head, in case he had got within him, and could by no other meanes have saved his owne. That confidence he pretends that neither <hi>John the Baptist, nor Paul would doe so,</hi> supposing all circumstances should have paralell'd (for otherwise he speakes to little purpose) is but the inspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Chaire, neither doth he so much as plead or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, any better ground for it.</p>
               <p>But the Bishop himselfe (it seemes) makes no great treasure of this answer of his neither, but (in effect) grants, that it is very likely that the Prophet would have served the Cavalier neither better nor worse, then as the Anti-Cavalier concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth he would have done, had matters come to that exigent he proposeth; and therefore (in the third and last place) hee casts out his sacred Anchor, betakes himselfe to his bottome answer, the best of all the strength he had to oppose, which is this; That <hi>Elisha was a great Prophet, and had the spirit of</hi> Elijah <hi>doubled upon him; and those actions that he did, or might have done, through the inspiration of Gods spirit; this man may not doe, except he be sure of the like inspiration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Answer, <hi>Elishas being a great Prophet, and having the spirit of</hi> Elijah <hi>doubled upon him,</hi> hindreth not at all, but that the Anti-Cavalier, yea and the Philo-Cavalier too, may doe, yea and ought to doe, <hi>hic et nunc,</hi> consenting, many things which hee did, and might have done by the inspiration of Gods Spirit; yea many things, without asking the consent of <hi>hic et nunc</hi> themselves. I presume <hi>Elisha</hi> prayed unto God, loved God and men, by the inspiration of Gods spirit: and will not the Bishop allow either himselfe or others, to doe these things, as well as hee? I confesse Bishops have bin very chary and tender in granting this liberty; and where it hath bin taken over-deepe, the High Commission hath made transgression and money of it.</p>
               <p>Yea but the Bishop meanes the extraordinary inspiration of the Spirit of God; and supposeth that the Prophet did what hee did in the premisses, by such an inspiration; and hereupon concludes his example to be no pattern or warrant for imitation.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:197154:25"/>
               <p>I Answer, if this be the meaning. then have at the Butcher with his owne Hatchet; why doth he (a few lines before as we heard) say, that <hi>the Prophet in his judgment did, in what he did, but little more then what God and nature alloweth every man to doe?</hi> And why doth he say a few lines after, that <hi>indeed the place is plaine, that</hi> Elisha <hi>made no other resistance, but what every man may lawfully doe,</hi> &amp;c. Surely he that saith these things doth not thinke that <hi>Elisha</hi> did what he did, in the particulars so much insisted upon, by <hi>extraordinary inspiration</hi> of the spirit of God. The truth is, that there are no fewer then three notorious inconsistencies or contradictions, within the compasse of this his answer. First, <hi>his judgement is, that the Prophet did a little more (though but a little more) then what God and nature al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth every man to doe,</hi> Secondly, his judgement (contrary to that) is, <hi>that the place is plain, that he made no other resistance, but what every man may lawfully doe.</hi> Thirdly, his judgement (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to both) is, <hi>that what</hi> Elisha <hi>did in this case, he did it by the extraordinary inspiration of the Spirit of God.</hi> He that thus turnes himselfe every way, and cuts and slasheth himselfe (like <hi>Baals</hi> Priests) for an answer, is it not a plaine signe that he knowes not which way to turne him for an answer to purpose? The common saying is, <hi>Nusquam est, qui ubique est.</hi> And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding as if he had quitted himself like a man and laid his adversary flat, hee comes downe from the theatre with this triumphant song in his mouth; <hi>yet this man would inferre hence, that we may lawfully, with a strong hand, and open warre, resist the authority of our lawfull King.</hi> The truth is, that for any thing the other man hath answered or said, this man or any other man, may inferre from the premisses what they will. But he that gives power and authority to a King, <hi>to doe what he pleaseth,</hi> p. 29. here takes the like power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to himselfe to speake what he pleaseth. A Reverend Bishop would bee ashamed to lay his mis-begotten Childe at an honest mans doore. Verily you deserve to sit no more in Parliament, till you can shew, where the Anti-Cavalier hath made such an inference as you charge him with, viz: <hi>that we may lawfully, with a strong hand and open warre; resist the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of a lawfull King,</hi> and if you be kept out till then, your
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:197154:25"/> returne will be <hi>ad Calendas Grecas,</hi> the very punctuall precise time desired by all true lovers of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> for your re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement thither. The <hi>Anti Cavalier</hi> never thought it never spake it, never delivered it by pen or otherwise, that it was lawfull for us or any man to resist the authority of a lawfull King. Therefore the Bishop goes out in a snuffe here.</p>
               <p>Yet afterwards, <hi>p.</hi> 62. he would faine have somthing to say, but that he knowes not well what, to those same <hi>almost two leaves,</hi> which the Anti-cavalier, <hi>spends in six severall answers,</hi> that <hi>hee makes to an objection against the examining of the equitie or iniquity of the Kings commands.</hi> Against these <hi>almost two leaves</hi> he gives sentence <hi>pro tribunali,</hi> that they are <hi>spent to no purpose.</hi> If I thought so, my advice should be to have them bound with the Bishop of <hi>Ossoryes</hi> Grand Rebellion: for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one booke troubled, then two.</p>
               <p>But is he as strong in his evidence as he is in his judgment? Not by as many degrees as the Sun went back in the Diall of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> in Hezekiahs dayes. Make the computation and see. The indictment you have heard already, it is for the crime of <hi>impertinency;</hi> the evidence is, <hi>because we never deny, but that in some cases, though not in all (for there must bee</hi> Arcana Imperij, <hi>and there must be privy Counsellors; and every Peasant must not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine all the Edicts of his Prince) the commands of Kings may not onely be examined, but also disobeyed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>By the connexion of this reason with the accusation, which it is brought to prove, it seemes the Bishops opinion is, that nothing is written <hi>to any purpose,</hi> but what is written in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to him, and men of his order. For the reason which he gives, why the <hi>almost two leaves</hi> are written or <hi>spent to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,</hi> is fairely this, <hi>because</hi> he and his Copes-mates <hi>doe not deny</hi> what is there proved. And for this opinion of his, I can ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry freely goe thus farre along with it, as to thinke, that as the condition and times of the Gospell are for the present, there can nothing lightly be written to better purpose, then what is and may be written in opposition to him and his Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall com-rades. But if his opinion be (as his reason gives it) that nothing is written to any purpose at all, except it puls some or other of his opinions by the throat, I professe inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuously
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:197154:26"/> that I have not so bad an opinion of the man, as to set the foot of my judgement by his, in this. I believe hee holds many Orthodox and savoury truths, which may bee handled and pleaded for to very good purpose.</p>
               <p>Nor Secondly, doe I apprehend that reason of his to bee of sufficient strength, which he gives why we should make such a distinction or difference betweene a Kings commands as this, that some should be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, others <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, some liable to examination; others priviledged and exempt. This reason is, (as hath bin said) because there must be <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Imperij,</hi> and <hi>Privy Counsellors:</hi> why, may not a man eat Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, without disturbing the Bishop at his rost Beefe? I would fain know, how any examination of any of the Kings commands whatsoever, as farre as concernes the lawfullnes of them in point of execution (and other examination was never dream't of by the Anti-Cavalier) should any wayes prejudice or trench upon <hi>Arcana Imperij,</hi> or secrets of State, Kings &amp; States may have their secrets, without any impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment either of their number or secrecy, and yet command nothing to be done or put in execution, but what may safely be so farre considered, and thought of, by those to whom the execution is injoyned: as whether they be lawfull to be done by them, or no: The intention of the King or State, in what they command, is not necessary to bee knowne or inquired into, by those that are commanded (especially when either in the judgment of reason or charity, it may be presumed to be good) because it is onely the nature and substance of the act injoyned, that concernes the inferiour, or servant that is to performe it; But these he ought still so farre to examine and inquire into till hee discovers either lawfullnesse or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfullnesse in them, and accordingly, either to obey, or to refuse the command. And if there were any such secrets of Kings and States, which required subjection unto their edicts and commands; upon any such termes, that those that are to obey, must not so much as consider, whether it be lawfull for them to obey or no; and to resolve either of obeying or not obeying accordingly; better were it a thousand times that all such secrets should bee prophaned and cashiered, then
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:197154:26"/> maintained or regarded by either. Never let Kings or States thinke to prosper or thrive in greatnesse, by the Revenues or incomes of such <hi>Arcana,</hi> which cannot be managed but with sin and disobedince unto God.</p>
               <p>Thus still we see, that Episcopall batteries and assaults are of no value to pierce or shake the fortifications and bulwarks which the Anti-Cavalier hath raised for the defence of the cause undertaken by him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. IV. <hi>Wherein the third assault made upon the Anti-Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier by the Cavaliering</hi> Bishop, <hi>is examined, and the Anti-Cavalier faire ly acquitted, either</hi> from throwing dirt in the Fathers faces, or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honouring that noble Army of martyrs, which our Church confesseth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Philo-Cavalier, in the beginning of his tenth Chap. <hi>p.</hi> 78. having risen early to commend himself and make a vaunt of what further learning he had yet in banke, for the maintenance of his cause, if need were, hee presently easeth his foule stomacke, by disgorging this vomit in the Anti-Cavaliers face.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the Anti-Cavalier, would perswade the World that all those learned Fathers, and those constant Martyrs, that spent their purest blood to preserve the purity of Religion unto us, did either belie their owne strength or befoole themselves with the undue desire of over va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued Martyrdome. But now they are instructed by a better spirit, they have cleerer illuminations to inform them to resist (if they have strēgth) the best and most lawfull authority, that shall either oppose, or not consent unto them. Thus they throw dirt in the Fathers face and dishonour that glorious companie; and noble Armie of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:197154:27"/>
               <p>I see men may rub their foreheads to what degree of hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse they please; and by applying stupefactives to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, make them sleepe to what depth of insensiblenesse they desire. Bishops surely are more afraid of scruples and qualms of conscience, then they are of Hell fire they provide so substantially against the one, by exposing themselves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare or regard unto the other. A man would have thought, that what the Anti-Cavalier hath written touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fathers and Martyrs in the premises, being extant; and for every man that desires to looke upon, should have bin a bridle in the lips of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s mans pen, to have kept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t from breaking out in such notorious slanders and untruths. But, <hi>pacta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>a est:</hi> he hath adventured upon a Bishopricke, and 'tis now too late to thinke of uprightnesse. The best ground he could have to utter himselfe as he hath done here, was a hope, that they that loved the spirit of his discourse, and would read with gladnesse what hee hath written, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vouchsafe to bestow time or paines in reading or conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what the Anti-Cavalier hath said. And the truth is, that there needs none other Answer or confutation to those lines of slander lately recited, but onely the laying of those passages in the Anti-Cavalier by them, whereunto they relate.</p>
               <p>For 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Where doth the Anti-Cavalier go about <hi>to perswade the World, that all the learned Fathers and constant Martyrs, did ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bely their owne strength, or befoole themselves with an undue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of over valued Martyrdome?</hi> The charge is so groundlesse, and the spirit of it so irrelative to any thing that the Anti-Cavalier hath written that it is hard to conceive, what pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage it is, that should give the occasion of it. The Bishop in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed cites in his Margent, <hi>Anti-Cavalier: p.</hi> 17. 18. &amp;c. But in all this wood I can find none of the Serpents he speakes of. It is true the Anti-Cavalier laies it down <hi>p.</hi> 17, 18. as matter of probality, <hi>that in case the Christians under the heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors had bin able enough to have defended themselves, and to have opposed the Emperour and his Party; yet that all christians scattered up and downe the Empire, might not have this apprehension of their strength, or thinke themselves strong enough to resist their Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:197154:27"/> And some lines after; <hi>that it was no wayes necessary that they should be all of the same mind and judgement, touching the suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of their strength; and that upon: his ground it might bee, that nothing was attempted in way of resistance by them.</hi> This is the utmost line and pin of all that the Anti-Cavalier saith in the pages cited by the Bishop, or elsewhere, touching this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. Now I would know of a man that had not made shipwrack of his forehead, whether there bee in all this, so much as an appearance of any such designe, as <hi>to perswade the World, that all the fathers and Martyrs did belie their owne strength?</hi> When as it is expresly granted and supposed, that a great part of the Christians then living, might have an apprehension of the sufficiency of their strength for resistance? Besides, that any one either <hi>of the fathers</hi> or <hi>of the Martyrs,</hi> should doubt or question their strength in this kind, is not so much as whispered or intimated in the lowest manner, in all that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course. Therefore to charge the Anti-Cavalier, that hee should goe about <hi>to perswade the World, that all the Fathers and Martyrs should belie their owne strength;</hi> when he imputeth no such thing to any one of them, is a slander worthy that order of men from whence it comes, whose tongues and pens not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding (in the sence of our English Proverbe) are no slander.</p>
               <p>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. That he should desire to <hi>perswade the World, that all the fore-named Fathers and Martyrs should befoole themselves with the undue desire of overvalued Martyrdome,</hi> is as farre from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable construction that can be made of any thing affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by him, as the former charge was. The Anti-Cavalier supposeth it indeed <hi>(page</hi> 20, 21. of his Discourse) as a thing possible that <hi>God might conceale</hi> a particular <hi>truth in this kind, from the guides and teachers of his Church in those times,</hi> and gives such reasons for this his supposition, as the Philo Cavalier (I beleeve cannot take away. 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Hee further supposeth, <hi>that that spirit of courage, patience and constancy, which God powred out abundantly upon his Church and servants in those times, whereby they were so strengthened and incouraged to suffer that Martyrdome, seem'd a desirable thing unto them, might be an occasion to take them off from inquiring into their lawfull libertie of declining it.</hi> And of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:197154:28"/> this supposition also he gives such an accompt, as the Bishop hath no mind to examine 3<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. He supposeth; <hi>that whilst there lay a confessed necessitie of suffering upon Christians,</hi> 1. <hi>till the supposed strength of resistance came to them (which could not bee much lesse then.</hi> 200 <hi>yeers) Martyrdome was so extolled and magnified by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall acclamations, continuall Panegericks and orations made in the praise thereof, that probable it was, that no man for a long time would have bin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ured, that should have taught any doctrine that might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waies seeme to take men off from the desire thereof.</hi> This suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition I suppose the Bishop himself will not oppose. 4<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. (and lasty) he supposeth <hi>that the frame and tenor of Gods after disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations</hi> (viz: as touching Anti-Christs advancement into his Throne) <hi>did require, that such a libertie</hi> as hee had spoken of, <hi>should be hid</hi> from his Church <hi>or at least that they should not make use of it,</hi> In case they had seen it, and had had opportunity, in respect of outward strength to have used it: <hi>as on the contrary the nature and purport of those dispensations, which God hath now in hard requires that this liberty should be manifested and made known unto Christians.</hi> This Supposition hee further explaineth and proveth, <hi>p.</hi> 21, 22. of that Discourse. Now set malignity her selfe doe her worst, and breake all the rules of charity seven times over (if she please) only let her observe and keep to rules of Grammar; and let her say what there is in all these passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or suppositions, that carrieth any shew or colour in it to prove that the Anti-Cavalier goes about <hi>to perswade the World that all the Fathers and Martyrs befoold themselves with an undue desire of overvalued Martyrdome: or that he throws dirt in the face either of the one, or of the other.</hi> He doth not in all these parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, so much as once positively affirme, that either the one or the other of them were either ignorant of that liberty he speakes of or over-valued Martyrdome; onely he suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth a possibilty of both.</p>
               <p>But suppose he had affirmed both positively, doth it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, bat therefore he represents <hi>all the Fathers and Martyrs,</hi> as men <hi>that had befoold themselves?</hi> Indeed by the Logicke of him that is the inference-maker <hi>quidlibet,</hi> will follow <hi>ex que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet.</hi> His best Logicke (it seemes) consists in a Court of fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties kept in his owne breast out of which hee can dispence
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:197154:28"/> with spurious and illegitimate consequences when hee pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and give them a capacity of being thought Rationall and cleere.</p>
               <p>Doth every man, or any man, that hath not attained the knowledge of some particular conclusion or truth in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, therfore befoole himselfe? I presume the Bishop is <hi>nesci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent</hi> (not to rub him with the course towell of <hi>Ignorance</hi> where with notwithstanding hee bescrubs the poor Anti-Cavalier over and over) but <hi>nescient</hi> I say (doubtlesse) hee is, of many truths lying within the compasse of Divinity, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: will he therfore kindly accept of such a salutation as this from any man: Sir you befoole your self in I know not how many things? Or though his patience and humility be so profound as to take such an <hi>Ave</hi> kindly himselfe yet is it no wayes consistent with either, for <hi>him to</hi> speake to others in so course a Dialect.</p>
               <p>It is no disparagement to any man that is yet within the verge of mortality to have the circle of his knowledg thought narrower and lesse, the vast circumference of things to bee known. Nor is it any blot upon the Name or memory of him that was sometimes mortall to say of him, that he knew not all things. Because this being interpreted, is no more then to say that he was mortall.</p>
               <p>But the Bishop being a Father himselfe, and thirsting as it seemes) after the title of being thought a man omniscient, cannot indure to heare, that those that are known by the Name of Fathers, should be suspected to have bin ignorant of any thing.</p>
               <p>But because in this encounter he quits his intellectuals and falls on with his patheticals onely rayling and not reasoning at all: I will be at no farther expence of words upon him, for the present.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:197154:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Wherein the</hi> Bishops <hi>fourth incounter with the Anti-Cavalier, in which he chargeth him with</hi> lies and slanders cast upon the King to make him odious to his Subjects, <hi>is examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Oyle in his Cruze being formerly spent, the Bishop here comes to his vinegar Bottle. Having run himself out of his small stock of learning before he was aware, with such lavish expence thereof as he made in opposing the Anti-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier by way of argument and reason, in his two first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters; hee is enforced to mannage his 3. latter with an inferiour element, and to furnish his pen with the rankest slanders and lies he could rake off from the Divells dunghill.</p>
               <p>For let himself say, whether he hath not irregularied both himself and his pen with these un-priestly lines, <hi>p.</hi> 95. <hi>of his Grand Rebellion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But as</hi> Absalon <hi>knew well enough, that to traduce his Fathers Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, was the readiest way to infinuate, and to wind himselfe into a good opinion with the people, and to make the King odious unto his Subjects: so these and all other Rebels will be sure to lay load enough of lies and slanders upon their governours, and so the namelesse Author of the Soveraigne Antidote,</hi> GOOWDIN, Burroughes, <hi>and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance more, such scandalous, impudent, lying Libells, have not blushed (which a man would thinke the brazen face of Sathan could not chuse but doe) so maliciously and reproachfully, to lay to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties charge the things which he never knew, and which all they that know the King, doe know to be apparant lies, and most abominable slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders against the Lords Vicegerent,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Bishop (it seems) is very ingenuous and charitable to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Sathan; Hee <hi>thinkes that his brazen face cannot chuse but blush, so maliciously and reproachfully to lay to His Majesties charge</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:197154:29"/>
                  <hi>the things which he never knew, as</hi> Goodwin, Burrowghs, <hi>and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance more have done.</hi> It is somwhat strange, how the man should come so much as to make conjecture, what <hi>Sathans bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen face</hi> should doe had he not borrowed it of him, and made an experiment of it himselfe in this kind. Except (haply) he hath gotten a face more brazen then his? which indeed must needs be, if there be that ingenuity in Sathans face, which this charity tempteth him to believe.</p>
               <p>For not to blush <hi>so maliciously and reproachfully,</hi> to lay on such loads, not of <hi>apparent</hi> but of APPARANT LIES and <hi>most abominable slanders, upon Goodwin, and Burrowghs,</hi> as here he hath done; requires more brasse in the forehead, I meane a farre higher straine of impudency, then not to blush at any thing which either <hi>Goodwin,</hi> or <hi>Burrowghs,</hi> hath charged the King withall. For these men are so farre from <hi>laying loads of lies and slaunders</hi> upon the King, in what they have written, especially the former, (and I conceive the latter every whit as capable of the same purgation) that they have endeavoured upon all occasions, as farre as a good conscience would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, to ease such passages, with the fairest interpretation they could put upon them, as in the generall opinion of those a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst whom they live, reflected with some disadvantage upon His Majestie. And therefore <hi>not to blush,</hi> to charge such men <hi>with abominable lies and slanders against his Majesty,</hi> requires a face more <hi>brazen,</hi> then that which himselfe ascribes unto Sathan.</p>
               <p>I cannot bethinke my selfe, what piece of Wood it should be in the whole tract of Anti-Cavalierisme, of which this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer should make his <hi>Mercurie,</hi> or lying Statue. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon saying is, that <hi>Dolosut versatur in generalibus.</hi> They that mean to lie, or to deceive, you shall still find them in generals; because in such cases, the conviction or discovery is more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie made. They tell you they have a Needle of nine pence in a Bottle of Hay, disprove them if you can. The Bishop in his former encounter, somewhat honestly (as wee heard) cited the Anti-Cavalier, <hi>p.</hi> 17. 18 &amp;c. in his Margent, over against his charge: but here though his charge be seven times deeper, no lesse (as you have heard) then <hi>maliciously and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:197154:30"/>
                  <hi>to lay such things to His Majesties charge, as are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally knowne by all those that know him, to bee apparent lies and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable slanders,</hi> yet the bare credit and reputation of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty, is all the proofe or testimony you have from him, of the truth thereof. Hee makes accompt (it seemes) that the credit of his honesty is as authentique, and high prized in the world, as the Scribes and Pharisees, presumed thiers was with Pilate, to whom, being demanded <hi>what accusation</hi> they <hi>brought against Christ,</hi> being so eager in their prosecution of him they returned no other answer but this; <hi>If he were not an evill doer, wee would not have delivered him unto thee.</hi> So all the accompt <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 13. 13.</note> or evidence you must looke for from the accuser of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, of those hainous matters here laid to the charge of <hi>Goodwin</hi> and <hi>Borrowghs.</hi> and others by him, is onely this; that if they had done so and so hee would not have laid it to their charge. But Sir, let me tell you one thing (which may bee worth many a two that are told you otherwise) that if you would bee believed in your accusations and charges against godly men without proofe.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quare peregrinum, vicinia rauca reclamat</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg> i.
<lg>
                     <l>This Nation tells you with a loud consent,</l>
                     <l>That much might be if to another you went.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>For in this Nation your credit in this kind is broken in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like a potters vessell, whereof there remaines not so much as a sheard or piece, wherewith to take, either a little fire from the hearth; or a little water out of the pit. You and men of your order, have for so long a time, and so often, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed godly men falsely, that now your accusations only <hi>turne to a Testimony unto them,</hi> without further proofe.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Author of the Soveraigne Antidote.</hi> I know him not (at least by any relation to such a writing) but that he should be NAMELESSE, is one of the Bishops profound spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations. But because his meaning in the word (I suppose) is innocent and harmelesse, wee will not make him an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for a little Grammaticall acyrologie in speaking.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:197154:30"/>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Burrowghs</hi> I well know; and verily believe his glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings both in honesty and learning, to be better then the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates vintage in both. Nor hath his angry Lordship done any courtesie to speake of, to the Anti-Cavalier, in all his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, except it be in joyning him with Mr. <hi>Burroughs:</hi> but in this hee hath accommodated him with the like honour, wherwith the blind man restored to sight by our Saviour, 10. 9. Was gratified by the Scribes and Pharisees, who excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him, and cast him out of their society unto <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apostles. But were all the men he mentions, the <hi>namelesse Author, Goodwin, Burrowghs,</hi> and as many more as you will, were they (I say) all Angells from Heaven, yet if they doe but touch the mountaine of Episcopacie with the least finger of contempt they must be struck thorough with some Episcopall dart or other, and their names (at least) ston'd to death with the hardest &amp; roughest accusations that the great accuser of the Brethren can furnish his executioners with, for the service But this angry piece of Episcopacy affects (as it seemes) the glory of a true <hi>Achillean</hi> Cavalier, and then his impresse must be.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quae libet in quemvis opprobria fingere soevus,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg> i.
<lg>
                     <l>Advanc'd in choller, fiercely to revile,</l>
                     <l>Who 'ere comes in his way, with lying stile.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>I shall for (the present) onely desire this of the Ingenuous Reader, that the Anti-Cavalier may stand right and straight in his thoughts, untill his Accuser hath made good that sore charge of his against him, I meane of <hi>laying such things to His Majesties charge</hi> which himselfe <hi>and all that know him, know to be apparent lies and abominable slanders.</hi> And when this Heaven falls he makes no question but he shall have Larks enough to feast the Bishop, and make him and himselfe perfect friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:197154:31"/>
               <head>CAP. VI. The Bishops last Encounter against the <hi>Anti-Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> Wherin he chargeth him, <hi>with little lesse then justifying any Rebellion against the King, and much admires that he with his fellowes is not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and transferred to the Kings Bench barre, and there arraigned</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Man by this time hath reasoned himselfe quite out of all his learning, reason, and patience into a moody cholerique and bloody passion. For sure if his wits or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science had bin within call, he would never have made presse worke of such rotten stuffe, as hee hath spread upon the face of his 97. <hi>page</hi> the spinning whereof runs thus. <hi>Then we grow so impudent as to justifie any rebellion against our King: as in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Goodwin <hi>and that seditious Pamphleter in opening the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous name of the Lord of Hosts, doe but a little lesse: for which appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Gods glorious name, and abusing the holy Scriptures to such abominable transgression of Gods holy Precepts, to instigate the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to warre against their Soveraigne, and to involve a whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into a desperate distraction: I doe much admire that they are not apprehended and transferred to the Kings Bench barre to be there ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, and condemned to be punished according to their deserts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wonder a little, how the Bishop came by his simples for this Receipt. Surely hee hath good correspondence with <hi>Pluto:</hi> for we have here beaten and stamp'd together, as the principall ingredients in the composition.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oris Cerberei spumas, et virus Echidnae,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg> i.
<lg>
                     <l>The foamy froth of <hi>Cerberus</hi> triple chaps,</l>
                     <l>Mixt with the poyson of a female Aspe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:197154:31"/>
               <p>Onely this I must confesse, that did he meane as hee speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth (but Episcopacie seldome dasheth his foot against this stone) in the first clause, it were an hopefull straine of inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity in him; for here in words, hee ingenuously rangeth himsefe, amongst those <hi>that are so impudent, as to justifie any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion against the King. Then we are so impudent,</hi> &amp;c. And yet againe on the other hand, speaking this of the Parliament (which it's evident from the lines preceding that hee doth) there is a straine of impudence even in this ingenuity. For what hath he to doe to joyne himselfe with the Parliament, as one of them, when as his whole Order is spued out from thence.</p>
               <p>Well, but the man is here in his Rhetoricalls, and wee doe him some wrong to make him speake Logique, that is, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and truth, against his will. His meaning is plain enough, <hi>viz:</hi> to charge the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> with <hi>so much impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as to justifie any Rebellion against the King.</hi> It was time for the Kingdome to make the mountaine of <hi>Samaria;</hi> the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prelacy I meane) to smoake, and to force them down, like lightening from the heaven of their power, when their spirits were so farre overgrowne with pride and insolency, as to challenge the Supreme Court of Justice in the Land, with the <hi>justifying of Rebellion,</hi> nay (which is a calumny whereunto no pen lightly but a Bishops, could have bin tempted or sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned) with the <hi>justifying of any Rebellion against the King.</hi> Why, how many kinds or degrees are there of Rebellion against the King? is the Parliament, or Parliament friends, so impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as to justifie them ALL, the worst, the fowlest, and most desperate of them ALL? He professeth admiration, <hi>that</hi> Goodwin <hi>and the seditious Pamphleter, are not apprehended and transferred to the Kings Bench to be there arraigned, and condemned to be punished according to their deserts</hi> (all which might bee done, and yet not an haire of their heads fall to the ground) but it is rather matter of double admiration, that such portentuous revilers and blasphemers of the highest powers and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that God hath placed over them, especially without the least occasion given, should not either be recompensed with vengeance revealed from Heaven, or be made examples of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:197154:32"/> deepest severity of the Justice of the Land, or otherwise bee dismembred and torne in pieces by the impatient rage and indignation of the people.</p>
               <p>But let us coole a little in this heat on both sides, and then to it againe, with somewhat more moderation. You talke much in your discourse, of resisting authority, and rising up against the lawfull authority of the King, of the hainousnes of Rebellion, with the like. But all this while you transgresse the old law or rule for arguing and discourse, which is this; <hi>Omnis disputatio debet à definitione proficisci:</hi> all disputations should begin with the definition of that, which is intended for the matter of dispute. Wee doe not understand, by any thing wee find from the beginning of your discourse to the end, what you meane by <hi>the Authority of the King,</hi> or by <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</hi> It may be you are best in the darke; and the light is to you that which <hi>Iob</hi> saith it is to Thieves, <hi>as the shadow of death,</hi> Job. 24. 17. The Scripture speaketh oft of authority, and condemneth Rebellion as a grievous sinne: but what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or rebellion is (to my best remembrance) it defineth not. We simple and well meaning men, conceive that the laws of every state and those who are authorized by these lawes, for their interpreters in doubtfull cases, are rather to be advised with, about the nature of that authority which is lawfull &amp; lawfully setled in every State or Kingdom respectively, and so about the nature of Rebellion, then with Divines, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally those of the chayre. The Scriptures command that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice be done on all hands and that no mans right be deteined from him: but whether this house or inheritance that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily is in question between severall pretenders, be the right of the one, or of the other, it determineth not at all: but lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth this to be adjudged by the Lawes, or vice-Lawes (I mean the customes of the State) wherein the question falleth. In like manner, what the Authority or lawfull power (for these I judge to be much the same) of the King of England is, and so what the lawfull power of an English Parliament is, is not to be found by searching the Scriptures though never so nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly: the English Lawes are the Oracles that must be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted with for the knowledge and determination of these.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:197154:32"/> And so likewise it is for matter of Rebellion. And in case there ariseth any question betweeene partie and partie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning either, which the first letter of the Law (as I may call it) is not able to determine or reconcile; then the second let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Law, <hi>i.</hi> the persons nominated or authorized by the Law, or at least by such a custome as is authorized by the Law for her interpretation in such cases, is to determine it. In case there be a subordniation of such persons, and the resolution of the inferiour be not yet satisfactory, recourse must be had to the supreame in whose award there lies a necessity upon both sides and parties to acquiesce and rest, there being no possiblity of any farther appeale, but unto God himselfe. And what the resolution of the Supreme Judicatorie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed or countenanced by the Law, in such cases of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or question shall be is to be look'd upon &amp; judged as the resolution of the law it self, yea <hi>of the known law of the Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this chain will hold (and I believed that all the force and strength of all the Episcopall learning in the land will not be able to breake the weakest linke of it) then look to your selfe, least you and your fellow Cavaliers, be in due time drawn by it to <hi>the Kings Bench barre</hi> you speak of, <hi>to be there arraigned and condemned to be punished according to your deserts;</hi> Which (I feare would be found another manner of punishment, then what either the Anti-Cavalier, or Pamphleter you speake of have deserved. For there is no law of the Kingdom better known, then that the high Court of Parliament is the Supreame Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory of all Questions and disputes in law, against, and from whom there lieth no appeale to any other Judge or Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory but onely to another of the same, I meane another Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And therefore it is they, not you, that must deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and define, what lawfull authority, and what Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in <hi>England.</hi> Therefore Sir, you are fallen into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire of the old Proverb, <hi>Sutor ultra crepidam</hi> having plaid <hi>the Cobler beyond your Last, to Arraigne and condemn</hi> at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, for resisting lawfull Authority, and for Rebellion, which are crimes of another cognizance; and from which they, to whom the cognizance and Judicature of such mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters properly belong have not only acquitted the persons by you <hi>arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and condemned,</hi> but have laid your waller upon your owne neck, and have concluded, <hi>stop the Thiefe,</hi> to be the Thiefe himself.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:197154:33"/>
               <p>And whereas you hope to be relieved by the Kings absence from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and think their resolutions and determinations without him to be invalid and insufficient, you must know that this is but to few fig leaves together to cover your nakednesse. For,</p>
               <p>1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. This being a case and question in law, what if the <hi>Parliament</hi> it self should give sentence against you? Your fig leaves are gone.</p>
               <p>2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. Those that understand the Laws of the Kingdome better then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you or I wil tel you, that though the King may be personally absent from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> (<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>See the Trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tise intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the disloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists to their Soveraignes,</hi> &amp;c. p. 21. &amp; p. 41. &amp;c.</note>) yet legally he cannot. <hi>The King</hi> (say they) <hi>in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of law, is ever legally present, in, and with his Parliament when they sit, wherever his person is: and his Royall legall will (of which alone the law takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice) is ever presumed to concurre with his greatest counsell the Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As in all other Courts of Iustice, all proceedings are entred</hi> coram Rege, <hi>though the King never yet sate personally in any of them, as he hath oft times done in this Parliament.</hi> So that you cleerly see, that neither the Kings absence from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor yet his refusing to give his personall consent to their votes and determinations, will any waies acquit you, from being both a Traytor and Rebell, in case the <hi>Parliament</hi> shall adjudge you either.</p>
               <p>3<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. And lastly, in case the authority of Parliament, still including (as we heard) <hi>the Royall legall will, and consent of the King,</hi> bee found and proved, to be the Supream authority, or highest pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Land, let <hi>Gr. Williams</hi> the Lord Bishop of <hi>Ossory,</hi> and all the Cavaliering Bishops and all co-operating Papists, and others who oppose the Parliament, know, that they, and none other but they are the men, who <hi>resist the higher powers,</hi> &amp; consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>shall receive to themselves that damnation,</hi> which the Apostle threatneth, <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2.</note> except they repent.</p>
               <p>And if the said <hi>Gr: Williams</hi> would not have it thought or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that the authority of Parliament, is their highest authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and power in the Land, and consequently that himself and his Copes-mates are <hi>Rebells,</hi> and the men that <hi>have involved the whole Kingdom into a distraction,</hi> let him acquit himself like a man, and substantially answer, those fourteen Arguments, which are laid down and argued at large to prove it, by the Author of the Discourse formerly mentioned, entituled: <hi>The Treacherie and disloyaltie of Papists to their Soveraigns in Doctrine and practise,</hi> &amp;c. from p. 17. of the said Discourse to the end.</p>
               <p>When the Bishop hath honestly, and with currant money a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst understanding men, paid this reckoning, it is like the Anti-Cavalier shall be willing to trade further with him upon a new score. But in the meane time, I professe ingenuously, that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:197154:33"/> I know not how to help it, but that he and his, must be look'd upon, as guilty of those hainous crimes, wherwith they so fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge their innocent adversaries, I meane, <hi>Rebellion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting lawfull authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas, in this encounter, hee layeth it to the charge of the Anti-Cavalier, that: <hi>he abuseth the Scripture;</hi> I answer, that all his guilt in this kind lyeth in his being accused. When his accuser shall permute his effeminate affirmations for Masculine argumentations, and his raylings for reasonings, he shall bee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to addresse himselfe, either to a faire and thorow purgation of himselfe, or to an humble acknowledgment of his misprissions in this kind. But howsoever,</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quis tulerit Gracchos de seditious querentes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who can indure to heare, without disdaine,</l>
                     <l>The Gracchi of sedition to complaine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>What? Bishops complaine of men for abusing the Scriptures? When as (alasse) the abuse of Scripture is the foundation of their thrones. It is not by the milk, but by the blood of the Scriptures that this order of men is nourished and kept alive in the World. And as for this Episcopal blade, which we have now in hand, it is hard to say, whether he hath cited, or abused, more Scriptures in his <hi>Grand Rebellion.</hi> Certaine I am that in the generall, hee hath abused, <hi>tot quot,</hi> as many as he hath cited: for he hath ingaged them all against the Parliament, and Parliamentary proceedings, <hi>i.</hi> against the advancement of Gods glory in a peaceable and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall way of reformation. It were an endlesse task to grapple with him, about the sense and interpretation, of all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar texts of Scripture, upon which he hath laid violent and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive hands, in this discourse, There are six together cited, <hi>p.</hi> 49. of his discourse, all which we have already proved, to be meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abused and mistaken by him. How he hath abused that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, 2. <hi>Let every soule bee subiect to the higher power: and whosoever resisteth, resisteth the ordinance of God,</hi> by his conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of it, for the chiefe Sanctuary of himselfe and his fellow Cavaliers, sufficiently appeareth by what hath bin lately argued in this Chapter. In severall places, he toucheth at, <hi>Psal.</hi> 105. 15. <hi>Touch not mine anointed,</hi> to prove all Kings the anointed of the Lord, and immediately invested with their power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from him. Whereas it's evident from the former verse, yea, and from the scope and carriage of the whole Psalm, that this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:197154:34"/> was not spoken to any people concerning Kings, as if they were the Lords anointed, that might not be touch'd: but unto Kings themselves concerning a people (the people indeed of God) as being his anointed ones, whom it concerned even Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves not to touch in any way of injustice or offence. For in the very immediately preceding, he had said: <hi>Hee suffered no man to them wrong: yea, he reproved Kings for their Sakes. Saying, Touch not mine anointed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But this sence of this Scripture hath of late, bin largely and substantially vindicated by a more learned pen. I shall (for the present) leave his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Reader to his own observation, for more Scriptures abused by him.</p>
               <p>And for conclusion. I shall only desire my Reader, to take knowledge of the most bitter, envenomed, and bloody spirit of the man, who finds himselfe aggrieved (even to admiration) that others are not affected with the same bloody passion with him) that the <hi>Anti-Cavalier,</hi> and the Seditious Pamphleter (seditiously so called) <hi>are not apprehended, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned at the Kings Bench Barre, for abusing the Scriptures to instigate Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to Warre against their Soveraigne,</hi> that is, for perswading men by the Scriptures, to performe both to King and Kingdome such a service, as the wit of this mans malice know's not how to traduce under a more plausible Name, then of an <hi>instigating Subjects to war against their Soveraign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Suppose it were certainly knowne, that a Roche, Miter, pall, and Tippet did much endanger the life or soule of the Bishop that weares them, though the Bishop himselfe conceited otherwise, and thought himselfe the braver man and so much the neerer Heaven for having such caparisons upon him; doth he that seekes to devest him of these dangerous accoutrements, though against his will, deserve to be called his enemie, or to be thought a man that either wish'd or sough't to do him harme? For my part in case a Bishop should be mistaken in any thing that relates unto me, and should conceive that to be evill and dangerous unto me, which yet in truth is not, and upon this sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, should do his best to separate between me and the supposed evill; well might I judge him to be a man of no profound reach; but deem him an enemy, I thinke I should not, certain I am, that I should have no sufficient ground of such an expression of his towards me, so to doe. I have formerly as farre as by words I well know how to do, vindicated not the innocencie and loyaltie onely, but the affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse likewise of my intentions for good towards his Majesty: of this man will take Satans occupation out of his hand, and make me like himselfe, I meane malignant, whether I will, or no; his accusation will yet beare it's own charges, and what it takes from me (for the (present) before men, it will hereafter restore and adde unto me dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before God. And so fare-well <hi>Gr. Williams,</hi> L. Bishop of <hi>Ossory,</hi> or whoever thou art, that facest the world, and out-facest the truth, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this title.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:197154:34"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 12. for on, <hi>r.</hi> one. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>l,</hi> 30. for affirme, <hi>r.</hi> assume, <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 15. for Estate, <hi>r.</hi> State. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 26. for: <hi>r.</hi> ib. <hi>l.</hi> 31. for scrase, <hi>r.</hi> scarce. <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>l.</hi> 25: for his, <hi>r.</hi> their. <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>l.</hi> 17. for on, <hi>r,</hi> one. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l. ult.</hi> for modest, <hi>r.</hi> modesty. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>dele</hi> or. <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 22. for dencein <hi>r,</hi> dence in, <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 22. for aed, <hi>r.</hi> ed. <hi>l.</hi> 23. for man, <hi>r.</hi> a man. <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>l.</hi> 37, for his, <hi>r.</hi> this. <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>l.</hi> 12. for 2<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>r.</hi> 1<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>l.</hi> 24 for and, <hi>r.</hi> a. <hi>p.</hi> 38 <hi>l.</hi> 19. for annimate, <hi>r.</hi> animate. <hi>l. ult.</hi> for one, <hi>r.</hi> on. <hi>p.</hi> 39. <hi>l.</hi> 15. for incence. <hi>r.</hi> incense. <hi>p.</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 22, <hi>dele,</hi> a. <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>dele,; p.</hi> 47. <hi>l,</hi> 1. for precise <hi>r.</hi> and precise. <hi>l.</hi> 16. for judgment, <hi>r.</hi> indictment. <hi>l.</hi> 33. for times, <hi>r.</hi> terms. <hi>p.</hi> 51. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>dele</hi> un, <hi>p.</hi> 53 <hi>l.</hi> 19. for the, <hi>r.</hi> then the. <hi>p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 16. for had; <hi>r.</hi> had not <hi>l.</hi> 30. for cursed, <hi>r.</hi> cused. <hi>p.</hi> 59 <hi>l</hi> 2 for his, <hi>r.</hi> her, <hi>l.</hi> 18. for,; <hi>r.) p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 29. for their, <hi>r.</hi> the. <hi>p.</hi> 64 <hi>l.</hi> 6. for very, <hi>r.</hi> verse. <hi>l.</hi> 7. for to. <hi>r.</hi> to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are diverse others mispointings with some mispellings. Wherein the</hi> Reader <hi>is desired to befriend the</hi> Corrector <hi>with his paines and pardon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>